<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The people's impartiall, and compassionate monitor; about hearing of sermons: or, The worlds preachers and proselites lively painted out, for a person of quality; upon occasion of hearing two famous divines, whose transcendent wit, oratorie, and elegancie, made many at their wits end with admiration! Being a rare discovery to vndeceive the deceiver. / By R. Younge of Roxwell in Essex.</title>
            <author>Younge, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97256</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Y171</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1583_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208949</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867864</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867864</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170108</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97256)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170108)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 200:E1583[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The people's impartiall, and compassionate monitor; about hearing of sermons: or, The worlds preachers and proselites lively painted out, for a person of quality; upon occasion of hearing two famous divines, whose transcendent wit, oratorie, and elegancie, made many at their wits end with admiration! Being a rare discovery to vndeceive the deceiver. / By R. Younge of Roxwell in Essex.</title>
                  <author>Younge, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.B. for James Crumpe in Little Bartholomews Well-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>In the year, 1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 20".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Preaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170108:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE People's Impartiall, And Compaſsionate Monitor; About hearing of Sermons: OR, The Worlds <hi>Preachers</hi> and <hi>Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> lively painted out, for a perſon of Quality; upon occaſion of hearing <hi>two fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Divines,</hi> whoſe tranſcendent <hi>Wit, Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie,</hi> and <hi>Elegancie,</hi> made many at their wits end with admiration!</p>
            <p>Being a rare diſcovery to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndeceive</hi> the <hi>Deceiued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By R. YOUNGE of <hi>Roxwell</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Wee preach not our ſelvs, but Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, &amp;c.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Cor. 4.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>My ſpeech, and my preaching was not with entiſing words of mans wiſdom; but in demonſtration of the Spirit, and of power: That your faith ſhould not ſtand in the wiſdom of men, but in the power of God, &amp;c.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 2.4, 5, to 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>I am come in my Fathers name, and yee receive me not: if another ſhall come in his own name, him yee will receive,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Joh. 5.43. See 1 Joh. 4.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>London, printed by <hi>J. B.</hi> for <hi>James Crumpe</hi> in <hi>Little Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomews Well-yard,</hi> In the year, 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170108:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>TO THE TRULY NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE, AND DESERVEDLY HONORED S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>NATHANA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>EL BASILE:</hi> A WORTHY PA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TRON AND PATTERN OF WISDOM, JUSTICE, FOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TITUDE, PIETY, AND SINCERITY.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>R. Y. Dedicates this mean piece of his Labours, and wiſheth long <hi>life;</hi> many followers, with increaſe of all <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170108:2"/>
            <head>The Peoples impartial and compaſsionate Monitor, about hearing of Sermons. Or, the Worlds <hi>Preachers,</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelites</hi> lively painted out; for a Perſon of Quality. Upon occaſion of hearing <hi>two famous Divines,</hi> whoſe tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>Wit, Oratory,</hi> and <hi>Elegancy,</hi> made many at their wits end, with admiration.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>Section 1.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Much honoured Sir!</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccording to your Order, I have heard another of your <hi>famous Preachers,</hi> and will thereof give you an account, as I promiſed; And ſo, that hundreds I hope ſhall be the better for it.</p>
               <p>The truth is, I extreamly <hi>admire</hi> them both, though I <hi>honour</hi> them not at all: The one made as rare a <hi>ſomething,</hi> of <hi>nothing,</hi> as ever I heard. The other for his skill in <hi>Sophistry,</hi> is (I confeſs) a <hi>Non-ſuch.</hi> Both may be rare <hi>Preachers</hi> for ought I know; but as he ſaid of one <hi>little learned,</hi> and <hi>leſſe modeſt;</hi> who uſurped all diſcourſe at the Table: I never heard <hi>learning</hi> make ſuch a <hi>noiſe:</hi> So I never heard a ſolid Preacher, deliver ſo <hi>many words,</hi> for ſo <hi>little matter;</hi> ſo much <hi>Oratory,</hi> for ſo little <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well may theſe <hi>plaſhes of water,</hi> be held by ſome <hi>deep Divines:</hi> but I preſume you may <hi>gage</hi> their Divinity with one of your fingers. As for their Sermons, (for ſo men call them; though no otherwiſe then the <hi>Heathen Images</hi> are called <hi>gods:</hi> Nor are they more like Sermons, than <hi>Michaels image of goats hair</hi> was like <hi>David.</hi>) I may fitly liken them to <hi>a plume of feathers,</hi> for which ſome will give <hi>any thing,</hi> others juſt <hi>nothing.</hi> Or, if I compare them to a <hi>Nightingale tongue pye,</hi> (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing far more elaborate and coſtly, than profitable or nouriſhing;) it is a great <hi>Hyperbole.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Indeed as a <hi>Reverend Divine</hi> ſpeaks; if I had no other <hi>Miſtreſſe</hi> then <hi>Nature,</hi> I would wiſh no other <hi>Maſter</hi> then ſuch a <hi>Seneca, Cicero,</hi> or <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthenes:</hi> but being a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> I go not to hear the rarities of human <hi>Eloquence,</hi> but the eternal <hi>Word of God;</hi> and more to <hi>profit</hi> my <hi>ſoul,</hi> than to <hi>pleaſe</hi> my <hi>ſenſes.</hi> A <hi>wiſe man ſhould</hi> (yea, a <hi>good Chriſtian will</hi>) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound to himſelf ſome <hi>end,</hi> ſome <hi>good end</hi> of his going to hear: (for he that in his <hi>actions,</hi> propoſeth no mark, or main <hi>end</hi> to himſelf; is like a <hi>Ship</hi> that aimeth at no <hi>Harbour;</hi> and no <hi>wind</hi> makes for him, that hath no intended <hi>Port</hi> to <hi>ſail</hi> unto, neither can he expect any <hi>Voyage</hi> of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.)
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170108:3"/>And to what end ſhould any of <hi>Chriſts ſheep</hi> go to the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, but to <hi>hear his voice?</hi> which is <hi>ſpirit</hi> and <hi>life</hi> to <hi>quicken</hi> thoſe that are <hi>dead</hi> in ſin; and to <hi>raiſe</hi> up thoſe that are therewith <hi>caſt down.</hi> Yea, the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is <hi>the ſtrong arm of the Lord; and the mighty power of God to ſalvation, to every one that beleeveth,</hi> Rom. 1.16. And therefore they never go to hear it, but in hope to be the better for it: Namely, that they may have their <hi>faith</hi> ſtrengthned by it, or their <hi>patience</hi> increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or their <hi>judgement</hi> rectified, or their <hi>wills</hi> reformed, or their <hi>life</hi> and <hi>practiſe</hi> bettered, or their <hi>love</hi> and <hi>zeal</hi> inflamed. But certainly, if any ſhall go to hear ſuch Preachers as theſe, (bear with my boldneſs I beſeech you) to any, or either of theſe ends, he ſhall no leſs ſail of his expectation, then did thoſe <hi>gueſts which</hi> Caligula <hi>invited to his golden banquet;</hi> which being ſet before them, did indeed delight the <hi>eye,</hi> but neither pleaſed the <hi>pallate,</hi> nor ſatisfied the <hi>ſtomach.</hi> Nor do ſuch Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, more pleaſe the <hi>ear,</hi> then they ſtarve the <hi>ſoul.</hi> Their ſimple hearers, being like that <hi>Calf</hi> in the <hi>Epigram;</hi> which went with no ſmall appetite to ſuck the <hi>teats</hi> of a painted <hi>Cow.</hi> Or, rather like one, that <hi>whets</hi> his <hi>knife</hi> upon a <hi>chalk ſtone;</hi> which doth not <hi>ſharpen,</hi> but make it more <hi>dull</hi> and <hi>blunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea, it were <hi>well,</hi> if it were no <hi>worſe;</hi> for this is to be underſtood of the beſt of their Sermons: whereas the other may be reſembled to <hi>a poiſoned fountain</hi> in the way; which the innocent and <hi>thirſty paſſenger</hi> ſeeing, is glad to <hi>drink of;</hi> but in drinking, is ſure to <hi>dye</hi> for it. Yea, how many of theſe rare <hi>Preachers</hi> could I name? that ſerve their <hi>hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> (had they the wit to perceive it) as <hi>Buſirus</hi> (whom <hi>Herculus</hi> ſlew) ſerved the poor: who killed ſuch, as came to him for hoſpitality. Or, <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the <hi>Prince,</hi> who fraudulently called together ſeven thouſand innocent perſons, as it were to ſee <hi>playes,</hi> and then ſent in <hi>ſouldiers</hi> to <hi>ſlay</hi> them: For under a colour of <hi>feeding,</hi> and <hi>curing</hi> their ſouls, they <hi>impoiſon</hi> and <hi>kill</hi> them. Or, in caſe they be leſs cruel, and do anſwer the <hi>hunger</hi> and <hi>thirſt</hi> of an <hi>empty</hi> ſoul; it ſhall be no otherwiſe then the <hi>Jews</hi> did <hi>our Saviour,</hi> who <hi>gave him gaul for his meat,</hi> and in his thirſt <hi>vinegar to drink,</hi> Pſa. 69.21.</p>
               <p>But this being a truth, that tranſcends both the underſtanding, and beleef of all that are unacquainted with <hi>Satans wiles.</hi> (Nor can it be beaten into the brains of unbeleevers, who want the <hi>light of Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> and the <hi>eye of faith.</hi>) I have taken ſome pains, in painting out theſe <hi>Preachers,</hi> and their <hi>Proſelites;</hi> affirming no more then I know by grounded experience; and ſhall fully confirm from the <hi>Word of truth.</hi> Which commands us to <hi>try the spirits, and their doctrine, whether they be of God or no.</hi> Nor will you I hope, think the time ill ſpent, in your ſerious peruſal thereof. If it make you a <hi>gainer,</hi> give God the <hi>glory.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>All</hi> ſorts of <hi>Preachers,</hi> may be compriſed <hi>under four heads:</hi> for either they are,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170108:3"/>
                  <hi>Preaching</hi> Or, <hi>Non-Preaching</hi> Or, <hi>Un-Preaching</hi> Miniſters.</p>
               <p>Or, <hi>Preachers</hi> that are <hi>no Miniſters.</hi> Whereof I have to deal with <hi>Non-Preaching</hi> and <hi>Un-Preaching</hi> Miniſters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Non-Preaching Ministers,</hi> I might <hi>martial</hi> into many <hi>Bands:</hi> but the cheef are witty and <hi>Rhetorical Preachers:</hi> and to theſe, will I apply my ſelf in the firſt place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Witty</hi> and <hi>Rhetorical Preachers</hi> are ſuch, as Preach now and then, but it is to very little, or rather to no purpoſe. For, as they neither aim at <hi>GODS glory,</hi> nor the <hi>edification</hi> and <hi>converſion</hi> of their hearers, but their own credit, profit, and preferment: So their people are neither inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the <hi>myſteries</hi> of <hi>ſalvation,</hi> nor any whit reformed in their <hi>lives.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now theſe as preferring <hi>Abana</hi> and <hi>Pharpar</hi> before the River of <hi>Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan,</hi> chuſe rather to feed their people with the <hi>Onions</hi> and <hi>Melons</hi> of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſpeculations than with the ſpiritual <hi>Manna</hi> of GODS Word. Which is the cauſe their hearers have ſuch lean and hunger-ſtarved ſouls. There be a world of <hi>unhallowed Divines,</hi> that being ſent to ſue for GOD, wooe for themſelves. For all their aim and end is, <hi>To ſet out their Learning and Reading, and to breed admiration of their wit and worth.</hi> With <hi>Gnatho,</hi> they are deſirous to pleaſe every mans humour: and therefore leſt their Sermons, or rather <hi>Orations,</hi> ſhould not be thought Learned enough; you ſhall have them ſo richly compounded of <hi>Divinity, Morality,</hi> and <hi>Policy;</hi> with ſo great aſperſion of all other <hi>Arts, and Dapled ſo full of Authorities</hi> from <hi>Poets, Orators, and Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers;</hi> and ſo <hi>stuft</hi> with <hi>rich, magnificent, pompous, and painted words, well-couched phraſes, Oratory Figures, and pathetical Metaphors:</hi> (For they run all upon <hi>Metaphors;</hi> and by their good wills, ſpeak not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>Figure.</hi>) Together with <hi>Hebrew, Greek, and Latine Sentences;</hi> That no <hi>Room</hi> can be afforded for <hi>Scripture.</hi> Yea, they <hi>ſcorn</hi> the <hi>grave Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,</hi> the <hi>ſtately Plainneſs,</hi> the <hi>Rich Poverty,</hi> that <hi>Humble Majesty,</hi> that ſhines in the <hi>Simplicity</hi> of the <hi>Scripture.</hi> The <hi>contemptible Courſneſſe of Scripture-phraſe grates</hi> their <hi>Delicate Ears,</hi> and <hi>offends</hi> their <hi>Queaſie ſtomachs.</hi> For they are not able to <hi>Peiſe,</hi> (and ſo not to <hi>Praiſe</hi>) how in <hi>Fewneſs of words,</hi> there is <hi>Fulneſs of Matter:</hi> That they are <hi>Thick and Short, Pithy and Pathetical: Breef,</hi> and yet <hi>Full; Conciſe,</hi> and yet <hi>Clear; Careleſs,</hi> and yet <hi>Accurate.</hi> Which men, if they cannot inſtruct GOD, how to deliver his mind better: yet they are not ſo <hi>Well pleaſed</hi> with the SPIRITS way of <hi>Expreſſion,</hi> as with their <hi>Own;</hi> when deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their <hi>Words</hi> by <hi>Weight,</hi> and <hi>Drawing</hi> their <hi>Notions</hi> into <hi>Knots,</hi> and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170108:4"/>
                  <hi>Borders;</hi> placing them like <hi>Checquer,</hi> or <hi>Fret-work;</hi> driving their <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> to ſo <hi>Even a Cadency,</hi> that they fall in a <hi>Juſt meaſure and ſound.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to give them their <hi>Due;</hi> Their <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> are ſo <hi>Curiouſly Couch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo Neatly Starched and ſet;</hi> Their <hi>Words ſo Ranked, and meetly mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall'd,</hi> as if they were <hi>a Kin</hi> to <hi>Him,</hi> whoſe <hi>Name</hi> is, <hi>Six-Hundred Sixty-Six.</hi> And yet excel they never ſo much in wit, learning, order, elegan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and phraſe: Admit they deliver their words in <hi>Wax,</hi> with a <hi>Soaring-ſublimity, of high Strains, and Choice Compoſures;</hi> Though it move <hi>Great Delectation of affection;</hi> Suppoſe they tranſport their hearers with the wind of words, and flouds of eloquence, wherein is more <hi>wit</hi> than <hi>art,</hi> and more <hi>art</hi> than <hi>uſe:</hi> yet they are but <hi>windy, frothy,</hi> and <hi>vain Preachers:</hi> yea, they preach no more in reality, then <hi>Harpocrates</hi> the <hi>Egyptian,</hi> who was always painted with his finger in his mouth. For as every ſound is not <hi>Muſick:</hi> ſo every Sermon is not <hi>Preaching.</hi> A main end of <hi>Preaching,</hi> is <hi>Converting,</hi> as the end of <hi>Fiſhing,</hi> is <hi>Catching.</hi> But their Sermons tend to no ſuch end. Well may theſe <hi>Cobwebs</hi> of wit and learning be curious and admirable for their fineneſs of thread and work; but they are of no ſubſtance or profit to the ſoul.</p>
               <p>For admit them dainty <hi>Moral</hi> Diſcourſes, ſufficient to ſatisfie the moſt <hi>curious car,</hi> or <hi>refined Auditory:</hi> yet they are as improper to the end be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, as were a <hi>bone</hi> for a <hi>child:</hi> for wherein is the ſoul <hi>bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitted,</hi> or <hi>comforted</hi> by a witty and Rhetorical Diſcourſe? Or, in caſe ſome do dote thereon, do they not reſemble <hi>Ixion?</hi> who embraced a <hi>cloud</hi> inſtead of <hi>Juno.</hi> Their Sermons being meer <hi>breath,</hi> which <hi>vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes</hi> ſo ſoon as <hi>ſeen:</hi> For as he ſaid of the <hi>Delphick Oracle; Quoties le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur, negligitur;</hi> It is not ſooner <hi>gotten,</hi> then <hi>forgotten:</hi> ſo may I of their Learned Orations. For as <hi>one nail</hi> drives out <hi>another,</hi> ſo <hi>one ſentence,</hi> and <hi>one Sermon</hi> drives out <hi>another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for their <hi>Converting</hi> of a <hi>ſinner,</hi> or <hi>building</hi> up of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> they know not what it means. Yea, He appeal to their own conſciences, whether in all their lives, they have ſo much as <hi>civilized,</hi> or <hi>philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed</hi> one drunken, deboiſt, and vicious liver, by this their manner of Preaching: or, can any one of their applauders ſay, ſuch a man hath made me an <hi>hater of vice,</hi> and a <hi>lover of virtue? hand credo.</hi> Yet this hath been familiarly effected, by meer <hi>Philoſophers</hi> upon their <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now if they are inſufficient to effect the <hi>leſſer</hi> work; what probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is there, they ſhould accompliſh the <hi>greater?</hi> of true and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all converſion, which is no other then a <hi>miracle:</hi> For no leſs true, nor miraculous, though ſpiritual, is our <hi>raiſing</hi> up from an <hi>eſtate</hi> of inward <hi>corruption,</hi> to the <hi>life of grace,</hi> then was <hi>our Saviours</hi> reſtoring of <hi>ſight</hi> to the <hi>blinde, hearing</hi> to the <hi>deaf, speech</hi> to the <hi>dumb,</hi> health to the <hi>ſick,</hi> yea, <hi>life</hi> to the <hi>dead;</hi> and whatever in this kinde he did by <hi>himſelf,</hi> while he lived, the ſame he doth ſtill by his <hi>Miniſters,</hi> through the <hi>mighty</hi> and <hi>powerful</hi> working of his <hi>holy Spirit,</hi> with his written <hi>Word.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:170108:4"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</head>
               <p>Nothing proved him to be <hi>God,</hi> more then his <hi>casting out of Devils:</hi> For there is <hi>no casting out of devils, but by the finger of God,</hi> Luke 11.20. Neither is that <hi>ſtrong armed man</hi> overcome and ejected, but by a ſtronger than he, <hi>verſe</hi> 21, 22. And is any ſtronger than he, but God alone? no verily. As for <hi>man,</hi> he is no way able to deal with him; witneſs <hi>Adam</hi> in his <hi>ſtate of perfection, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> And yet as then himſelf caſt out <hi>devils,</hi> by ſpeaking the words of eternal life: ſo now his Miniſters caſt them out, by applying the ſame Word; for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>reigning ſin</hi> we have, is <hi>a devil:</hi> as <hi>Baſil, Auſtin,</hi> and Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> affirm, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. <hi>John</hi> 14.30. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.2. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26. and of him that by the power of the Word, hath <hi>pride, covetouſneſs, drunkenneſs, whoredome, ſwearing, envy,</hi> or <hi>ignorance</hi> caſt out of him, or mortified in him; we may ſay as properly, as it was of <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> he hath ſo many <hi>devils caſt out,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now it were a ſtrange folly to think, that theſe Preachers ſhould caſt them out, and overcome them, with the <hi>carnal weapons of their warfare,</hi> which they borrow from <hi>men,</hi> and not from <hi>God:</hi> What cares the <hi>devil,</hi> ſo long as they bring <hi>wit</hi> inſtead of <hi>weapons?</hi> he fears them no more, hearing the words of their <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> and eſpying them to have no <hi>courage,</hi> no <hi>power,</hi> no <hi>zeal</hi> for the <hi>glory of God,</hi> no aim at the <hi>edification</hi> of their <hi>hearers,</hi> than an <hi>Eagle</hi> fears a <hi>Swallow,</hi> or a <hi>Laon</hi> a <hi>Lamb:</hi> but makes anſwer, as he once did to the <hi>ſons of Sevah, Jeſus I acknowledge, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aul I know, but who are ye?</hi> It is a ſilly <hi>Hare</hi> that will be caught with a <hi>Tabor;</hi> and their Preaching is as prevalent to the caſting out of <hi>devils,</hi> as is the <hi>hunting</hi> of an <hi>Hare</hi> with an <hi>Oxe,</hi> or as <hi>oyle</hi> is to the <hi>quenching</hi> of <hi>fire,</hi> or as <hi>ſmoke</hi> for curing the <hi>eye-fight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now we eſteem things good, according as they are proper for our uſe. The goodneſs of an <hi>Horſe,</hi> doth not conſiſt in his <hi>coſtly trappings,</hi> and a <hi>velvet ſaddle;</hi> but in his <hi>ſtrength</hi> and <hi>ſwiftneſs.</hi> What benefit is in a <hi>gilt armour,</hi> if it will <hi>not defend?</hi> or, to what purpoſe is a <hi>golden key,</hi> if it will not <hi>open the door? Hungry ſtomacks</hi> like not to be <hi>fed</hi> with <hi>flaſhy cates,</hi> but <hi>ſolid meat;</hi> whereby they accrue both <hi>ſtrength</hi> and <hi>growth;</hi> and ſuch as <hi>meat</hi> is to the <hi>body,</hi> ſuch is <hi>reading,</hi> and <hi>hearing</hi> to the <hi>ſoul.</hi> It is the <hi>Word of God</hi> only, which moves the <hi>conſcience,</hi> and ſaves the <hi>ſoul.</hi> And what <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> ſaid of other <hi>Sciences,</hi> and <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy,</hi> is more true of all <hi>other Arts,</hi> and <hi>Divinity.</hi> They that <hi>ſtudy the other,</hi> and <hi>neglect this,</hi> are like <hi>Penelopes wooers,</hi> that made love to the <hi>waiting-women. The Kingdom of God is not in word, but in power,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.20</p>
               <p>Again, every man ſeeks after thoſe that are <hi>skilful</hi> in their <hi>Art:</hi> who ſaith <hi>Seneca,</hi> will not rather deſire a <hi>skilful Phiſitian,</hi> or <hi>Lawyer,</hi> than an <hi>eloquent</hi> one; ſo a <hi>powerful, experimental Divine,</hi> is to be choſen, rather than a <hi>witty one:</hi> Otherwiſe a <hi>Minſtrel,</hi> or <hi>Muſician,</hi> will ſerve to <hi>pleaſe the ear,</hi> and <hi>ſtarve the ſoul,</hi> as well as a <hi>Miniſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for any <hi>spiritual nouriſhment,</hi> that redounds to the <hi>ſoul</hi> from their <hi>Sermons,</hi> they may be compared to a <hi>Briſtol ſtone,</hi> or a Saint <hi>Martirs
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170108:5"/>Ring,</hi> which ſeem to ſome of <hi>great value,</hi> but are ſcarce <hi>worth</hi> a <hi>groat.</hi> Or, to <hi>Hercules Club</hi> in the <hi>Tragedy</hi> of <hi>Menander,</hi> which was of <hi>great bulk,</hi> but the <hi>ſtuffing</hi> was only <hi>moſs,</hi> and <hi>rubbiſh:</hi> Or, to variety of <hi>meats</hi> and <hi>drinks,</hi> curiouſly <hi>painted;</hi> which look as though they would <hi>ſatisfie</hi> the <hi>appetite,</hi> and <hi>quench</hi> the <hi>thirst;</hi> but do only cheat the ſpeedy-ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching <hi>traveller,</hi> of his <hi>hungry</hi> hopes: as <hi>Zeuxis</hi> did the ſilly <hi>birds,</hi> with his lively limb'd <hi>grapes.</hi> So dealing with their Auditours, as <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leogabalus</hi> did, by a great number of <hi>poor</hi> people, whom he had <hi>invited</hi> to a <hi>feast;</hi> which when they came, he ſet before them nothing but <hi>meats,</hi> and <hi>drinks</hi> in their <hi>ſimilitudes.</hi> Or, to that which <hi>rometheus,</hi> with a great ſhew of <hi>religious devotion,</hi> made for <hi>Jupiter;</hi> wherein he preſented the <hi>bones</hi> of two <hi>Bulls,</hi> covered with <hi>Skin</hi> and <hi>ſinews,</hi> but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauding them of the <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>fat.</hi> Or, to <hi>painted fire,</hi> which at the firſt bluſh, may make a man judge it to be <hi>fire indeed:</hi> but if a man hold his <hi>hand</hi> to it, to feel for ſome <hi>heat,</hi> and to make trial by the <hi>effects,</hi> a child in underſtanding, will be able eaſily to judge, that it is but a <hi>dead image,</hi> becauſe the <hi>effects</hi> are <hi>wanting.</hi> In a word, they couzen the world with <hi>copper</hi> for <hi>gold,</hi> with <hi>glaſs</hi> for <hi>pearl,</hi> with ſeeming or <hi>ſhadow</hi> for <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> and ſell us <hi>breath,</hi> for the <hi>bread of life,</hi> to <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> us, and <hi>froth</hi> inſtead of <hi>cordial,</hi> and <hi>celeſtial water</hi> to <hi>comfort</hi> us; and ſo <hi>cheat</hi> us, whatſoever we give; for its dear of a <hi>farthing,</hi> that is good for <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi> And we may ſay of their <hi>Sermons,</hi> as the <hi>Apostle</hi> of <hi>Idols; They are nothing in the world,</hi> 1 Cor. 8.4.</p>
               <p>Or, if the <hi>hungry ſoul</hi> findes any thing to <hi>feed</hi> upon, it is but like a <hi>meal</hi> of <hi>Grafiſh,</hi> where is <hi>much picking,</hi> very <hi>little meat:</hi> or, a <hi>banquet</hi> of <hi>Kick-ſhawes,</hi> which neither make good <hi>bloud,</hi> nor beget <hi>ſpirits;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrengthen the <hi>ſinews,</hi> nor increaſe the <hi>marrow;</hi> but only procure <hi>luſt,</hi> make the belly <hi>flatuous,</hi> and <hi>ſwell</hi> the body.</p>
               <p>I need not ſtand to amplifie it, you finde in your own obſervation and experience, a great difference between theſe <hi>ſpeculative Preachers,</hi> and <hi>experimental Divines.</hi> As hear the one, that ſpeaks <hi>spiritual things</hi> in <hi>spiritual words,</hi> with <hi>spiritual devotion,</hi> and zeal; and you will be ready to ſay, with thoſe <hi>Diſciples going to Emmaus; Did not our hearts burn within us, while he spake?</hi> Luke 24.32. Or, with thoſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.29. <hi>He ſpeaks with authority, and not as the Scribes.</hi> Or, with him the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.24, 25. <hi>Who hearing the ſecrets of his heart made manifest, being convinced, falls down, and worſhippeth, ſaying; God is in him of a truth:</hi> Whereas hear one of theſe <hi>ſpeculative Divines preach,</hi> perhaps like a Diſcourſe of <hi>Philoſophy</hi> read, the <hi>invention,</hi> the <hi>eloquence,</hi> and the <hi>pertinency</hi> doth preſently move you, and <hi>tickle</hi> your <hi>spirit,</hi> but there is nothing moveth or <hi>pricketh</hi> your <hi>conſcience;</hi> for it is not to her they ſpeak. And indeed for the moſt part, when <hi>ſpeculative</hi> men <hi>preach</hi> of <hi>practical</hi> and <hi>experimental</hi> truths, it ſeems to experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as <hi>Phormio</hi> his argument of the <hi>wars,</hi> ſeemed to <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibal,</hi> no better then dreams and dotage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:170108:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</head>
               <p>Beſides, <hi>holineſs</hi> in a <hi>Preacher,</hi> gives <hi>addition</hi> to the <hi>matter;</hi> and is a great means to heighten liking in the hearer. It is much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in an <hi>Orator,</hi> when the <hi>ſoul</hi> ſeems to ſpeak, as well as the <hi>tongue.</hi> Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſays, <hi>Tully</hi> was admired more for his <hi>tongue,</hi> then his <hi>minde; Ariſtotle</hi> more for his <hi>minde,</hi> then his <hi>tongue;</hi> but <hi>Plato</hi> for <hi>both.</hi> And both together is more perſwaſive, in working on the ſoul it meets with; for he that hears, has only thoſe affections, that the ſpeaker gives him; and <hi>devotion kindles devotion,</hi> where it is not, as a <hi>live coal kindles a dead one.</hi> And it is very requiſite, that <hi>Ministers</hi> ſhould be <hi>exemplary</hi> in all they urge and teach; for the <hi>eyes</hi> of the whole Pariſh are upon the <hi>Paſtor;</hi> and then is there <hi>life</hi> in their <hi>doctrine,</hi> when there is <hi>doctrine</hi> in their <hi>life:</hi> Men in this caſe, as in other caſes of <hi>Manufacture,</hi> except they <hi>ſee,</hi> they will not <hi>beleeve.</hi> Their <hi>eyes</hi> muſt be <hi>taught,</hi> as well as their <hi>ears,</hi> Phillip. 4.9. <hi>Thoſe things which you have both learned, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and heard, and ſeen in me, doe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He that will <hi>caſt a ſtone at an offendor,</hi> muſt be <hi>free himſelf:</hi> before <hi>Samuel</hi> doth charge <hi>Iſrael</hi> with their ſin, he clears his own <hi>innocency,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. Shall a prophane liver, preſcribe rules of ſanctity, and <hi>piety?</hi> Shall an <hi>Officer</hi> that reforms the <hi>Tap-houſe,</hi> be himſelf found in a <hi>Brothel-houſe?</hi> Were it not ſtrange, that the <hi>Witch</hi> ſhould tell the <hi>Jugler,</hi> he hath a bad <hi>conſcience?</hi> Or, that the <hi>Hypocrite</hi> ſhould rail at the <hi>Player?</hi> Or, the <hi>Uſurer,</hi> challenge the <hi>Theef?</hi> Or, if ſo, will they not retort this anſwer? <hi>Phyſician heal thy ſelf,</hi> Luke 4.23.</p>
               <p>Neither is it enough for them, being converted, to be <hi>common lines</hi> in <hi>Christianity,</hi> or pious in ordinary: For ſo every <hi>private Christian</hi> is commanded to be, <hi>blameleſſe, and pure, and as the ſons of God without rebuke, Philip.</hi> 2.15. But Miniſters ſhould be as <hi>ſet-copies of ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to others, and <hi>ſhine as lights, among whom they live in the world.</hi> The <hi>Apostle</hi> exhorteth <hi>Titus,</hi> to <hi>ſoundneſſe of ſpeech, and uncorrupt doctrine; but above all things,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſhew thy ſelf a pattern of good works,</hi> as preferring them: and gives this for his reaſon; <hi>that he which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth, may be aſhamed, as having nothing concerning you, to ſpeak evil of</hi> Titus 2.7, 8. And the like in his <hi>Epiſtle to Timothy, Be thou,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>an example to them in word, in converſation, in charity, in ſpirit, in faith, in purity,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.12. his very converſation muſt preach. <hi>If thou wilt turn unto me, thou ſhalt convert,</hi> ſaith <hi>God</hi> to <hi>Jeremy,</hi> Jer. 15.19. im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying, that if he did not the one, he ſhould not the other: or, if he did ſome, as it is poſſible a wicked Miniſter may, yet nothing ſo many. And this is given as a reaſon of <hi>John the Baptists</hi> ſo great ſucceſs, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting of ſouls, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.16. <hi>He ſhall convert many of the children of Iſrael to their Lord God,</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Angel</hi>) why ſo? <hi>for he ſhall go before him in the spirit and power of Elias,</hi> ver. 17. who was a zealous, and holy man.</p>
               <p>I deny not, but a lewd and <hi>wicked Minister,</hi> may be <hi>a good Preacher,</hi> (as no doubt but <hi>Judas</hi> was) and ſo prove the means of <hi>ſaving others,</hi> and bringing them to <hi>Heaven,</hi> while in the mean time himſelf goes the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170108:6"/>other way. <hi>Our Saviour</hi> tells us, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.22. <hi>that many</hi> Reprobates <hi>will ſay unto him at the Reſurrection; Lord, Lord, have we not by thy name prophecyed, and by thy name cast out deviis,</hi> &amp;c? whoſe anſwer ſhall be, <hi>I never knew you, depart from me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>We ſee in nature, that a <hi>deformed man</hi> may <hi>beget a comely childe; a fool, a wiſe man;</hi> an <hi>iron ſtamp</hi> may <hi>coin gold;</hi> the <hi>whetſtone</hi> is <hi>blunt,</hi> yet it <hi>ſharpens</hi> other things; the <hi>wind</hi> is <hi>cold,</hi> yet it makes the <hi>fire burn;</hi> the <hi>skilful Rider</hi> will reap ſome ſervice of a <hi>resty</hi> and <hi>wind-broken Jade:</hi> and ſhall not <hi>God</hi> ſerve himſelf, by the worſt of men, when he pleaſeth? But ordinarily, (for we ſpeak not of what <hi>God</hi> can do) where the <hi>Spirit ſpeaks twice,</hi> by <hi>illumination,</hi> and <hi>ſanctification,</hi> he is more <hi>heard,</hi> then where he ſpeaketh but <hi>once.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that this is ſo, appears moſt plainly, by the palpable difference that is between thoſe <hi>Pariſhes,</hi> which <hi>God</hi> hath bleſt with a <hi>zealous, holy,</hi> and <hi>conſcientious Miniſtery,</hi> and thoſe other places, that have had <hi>good-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Paſtors,</hi> or <hi>Corinthian-reachers:</hi> for even in this very caſe, the <hi>wholeſomeneſſe of the place</hi> is beſt known by the <hi>complexion of the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants.</hi> And we know what the <hi>holy Ghost</hi> tell us, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4.9. and Iſa. 24.2. <hi>Like Prieſt, like People.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is both an <hi>happy,</hi> and pleaſing <hi>harmony,</hi> when <hi>ſaying</hi> and <hi>doing</hi> goe both together; and he perſwades to virtue <hi>moſt,</hi> who liveth <hi>beſt.</hi> For a <hi>Chriſtian converſation,</hi> is of the <hi>Scriptures</hi> the <hi>beſt,</hi> trueſt, and plaineſt <hi>Comment,</hi> or <hi>Expoſition. Good works</hi> are unanſwerable <hi>Syllogiſms,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible <hi>demonſtrations;</hi> and it is natural for men, to follow the <hi>law of fact,</hi> before the <hi>law of faith;</hi> a <hi>viſible pattern,</hi> rather then a meer <hi>audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble doctrine. Religion</hi> hath a <hi>truth,</hi> and a <hi>power</hi> in it; people will never beleeve the truth of a doctrine in our <hi>mouths,</hi> where they ſee not the power thereof in our <hi>lives.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Paſtors are the glaſſe, the ſchool, the book,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Where peoples eyes do learn, do read, do look.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The learned Paſtours words, though plain;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To plain men truth may preach:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But Paſtours pious practice doth,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A holy life them teach.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That doctrine is divine indeed,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That by good works, proves words:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>More harm do ill examples breed,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Than good words, good affords.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Briefly, we read that more <hi>Inſidels</hi> were won to the <hi>Chriſtian faith,</hi> by the virtuous and <hi>holy lives</hi> of the <hi>Primitive Preachers,</hi> then by the <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> which they <hi>taught.</hi> They made the <hi>world</hi> to <hi>read</hi> in their <hi>lives,</hi> that they did <hi>beleeve</hi> in their <hi>hearts;</hi> and cauſed the <hi>Heathen</hi> to ſay, This is <hi>a good God!</hi> whoſe <hi>ſervants</hi> are <hi>ſo good?</hi> Nor is this all; for with what zeal or devotion, can an unhallowed, and unſanctified Miniſter, preſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170108:6"/>his people to holineſs, exhort them to repent and beleeve? or, with what affections can he pray for, and before them? As for inſtance; he whoſe <hi>hunger</hi> hath <hi>tempted</hi> him to <hi>ſteal</hi> a <hi>Lamb,</hi> ſays but a <hi>cold grace</hi> to his <hi>ſupper:</hi> As for <hi>oppreſſors,</hi> and <hi>defrauders,</hi> how they give thanks to <hi>God</hi> for their wealth, I refer to <hi>your</hi> thoughts, and <hi>their</hi> own <hi>conſciences.</hi> For ſin is worſe than a <hi>theef in the candle:</hi> or, an <hi>obſtruction in the liver.</hi> Two or three reigning ſins clapt on the heels of a preſent devotion, is like a <hi>ſudden cold,</hi> after a violent <hi>heat:</hi> So with what affection can a laud Miniſter exhort his people to holineſs? when his <hi>life,</hi> yea, <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>conſcience,</hi> are continually caſting his <hi>doctrine</hi> in the <hi>teeth,</hi> with that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.21.</p>
               <p>Beſides, as by <hi>ſhining</hi> here in their <hi>life,</hi> and <hi>doctrine,</hi> they <hi>turn many to righteouſneſſe:</hi> ſo hereafter, they <hi>ſhall ſhine as ſtars for ever and ever, Dan.</hi> 12.3.</p>
               <p>Again, happy are the people that have ſuch a Miniſter; whoſe <hi>words</hi> anſwer his <hi>thoughts,</hi> and his <hi>actions</hi> his <hi>words!</hi> who are <hi>Auguſtines</hi> in their <hi>ſtudies, Chryſoſtomes</hi> in their <hi>Pulpits,</hi> and <hi>Timothies</hi> in their <hi>houſes;</hi> that adorn the <hi>ſoundneſs of Learning,</hi> with <hi>holineſs of life.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 5.</head>
               <p>But to proceed, for this I ſalute only by the way. To go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to <hi>comfort an afflicted ſoul, by a flouriſhing ſtyle,</hi> is as much as to preſent a <hi>noſe-gay of Violets,</hi> to one that is <hi>ſtarving,</hi> for want of meat. When the <hi>thirſty traveller,</hi> after much labour and grief, ſpies a <hi>fountain,</hi> he rejoyceth; but coming to it, and finding it <hi>dry,</hi> his <hi>joy</hi> is turned into <hi>ſorrow;</hi> and he is ready to curſe it for ſuch a mockery, as <hi>our Saviour</hi> did the <hi>fruitleſſe Fig-tree,</hi> when he was hungry. Suppoſe we are thirſty, and would <hi>drink;</hi> foul, and would <hi>waſh;</hi> hot, and would be <hi>cooled;</hi> our houſes are on fire, and we would have them <hi>quenched;</hi> if we come to the <hi>well</hi> with our <hi>buckets,</hi> and finde it <hi>empty,</hi> we know not whether our grief, or indignation be greater. To conclude, an holy ſoul will never frequent the <hi>Church,</hi> that hath ſuch a <hi>Preacher;</hi> but if he light upon ſuch a <hi>Preacher</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> that he frequents, he appears to him like an <hi>importunate Fidler,</hi> that without invitation, impudently <hi>thruſts</hi> himſelf into his <hi>chamber, draws,</hi> and <hi>playes,</hi> and will not be denyed; he may give it the <hi>hearing,</hi> and that's an high favour; but he dares neither <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> nor <hi>commend</hi> it.</p>
               <p>I know there is nothing more pleaſing to the <hi>carnal ear,</hi> then <hi>variety,</hi> be it but <hi>hogs-fleſh</hi> a little varied with <hi>ſawce:</hi> as <hi>Flaminius</hi> was ſerved by his <hi>Host.</hi> And that <hi>ſtomachs,</hi> which within one moneth, are <hi>weary of Manna,</hi> ſet more by <hi>ſallets</hi> and <hi>ſawces,</hi> and <hi>Kick-ſhaws, ſloſhes</hi> of wit, then <hi>ſubſtantial food,</hi> the <hi>Word of God.</hi> And let ſuch a <hi>Corinthian Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,</hi> ſpeak the abortive <hi>figments</hi> of his own <hi>brain,</hi> yet their ſuperſtitious applauſe ſhall be <hi>vox Dei, the voice of God, and not of man,</hi> Acts 12.22. Yea, it is ſtrange to ſee, how ſuch an <hi>Orpheus,</hi> by his melodious <hi>harping,</hi> will <hi>draw</hi> theſe <hi>stones, birds</hi> and <hi>beaſts</hi> after him; and what applauſe he ſhall have, it being their manner to <hi>arrogate</hi> to the <hi>instrument,</hi> and <hi>dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate</hi> from the <hi>agent.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:170108:7"/>
               <p> Yea, admit they underſtand not the Miniſter, (as many of them <hi>preach for few,</hi> becauſe <hi>few underſtand</hi> them; as <hi>Jerome</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>Plato</hi>'s wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings) yet all is one, or rather they extoll him the more; as <hi>a countrey fellow</hi> being askt, how he liked ſuch a Miniſter? Anſwered, I promiſe you <hi>neighbour,</hi> it was a good Sermon, but me thinks <hi>a</hi> little <hi>Latine</hi> would have <hi>edified</hi> well.</p>
               <p>Neither is it ſtrange, they ſhould gain ſuch <hi>applauſe,</hi> from men as <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> and <hi>graceleſs</hi> as themſelves: for how eaſily are <hi>wanton minds</hi> wrought upon? what <hi>wind</hi> is ſo weak, as not to move the <hi>fan?</hi> what <hi>toy</hi> will not win a <hi>childe?</hi> A <hi>minde</hi> foreſtalled with <hi>levity,</hi> is like a <hi>veſſel</hi> without <hi>bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>last,</hi> ſoon over-ſet.</p>
               <p>But what is the iſſue? Theſe Miniſters perceiving, how this <hi>bait takes,</hi> turn all their peoples <hi>food</hi> into <hi>ſawce;</hi> and like <hi>Lucians Jupiter,</hi> ſpend all their time in <hi>painting of butter-flyes wings:</hi> ſo turning <hi>verity</hi> into <hi>vanity,</hi> or rather <hi>the grace of God into wantonneſs,</hi> while they turn the <hi>word of grace</hi> into <hi>curiouſneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea, that they may excel in this kinde, they will turn all their <hi>ſtock</hi> into <hi>four or ſix Sermons,</hi> which ſhall ſerve their <hi>whole life</hi> at the <hi>Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity,</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> and as they travel abroad the <hi>countrey;</hi> reſembling ſome <hi>needy flaunting Goldſmith,</hi> who hath nothing in the <hi>inner room,</hi> but all on the <hi>cupboard;</hi> and theſe ſhall be of ſeveral kindes, that they may <hi>pleaſe all humours.</hi> One whereof ſhall ſavour of piety, that ſo he may act the <hi>hypocrite,</hi> when it ſhall make for his preferment; the ſecond, ſerve to vex the <hi>Round-heads,</hi> becauſe that moſt generally pleaſes; the <hi>remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> being <hi>harmleſs,</hi> but <hi>unprofitable,</hi> ſhall reſemble the <hi>herb John;</hi> which being put into <hi>pottage,</hi> gives no <hi>taste</hi> at all <hi>good</hi> or <hi>bad,</hi> but an excellent <hi>colour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Indeed he hath ſuch a mind to laſh the <hi>Round-heads,</hi> that beſides a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial <hi>ſupply</hi> from <hi>Satan,</hi> his learned <hi>Tutour,</hi> one of thoſe Semons ſhall coſt him more labour and ſtudy, than all the reſt. As it is no hard matter for them to produce <hi>Elephanti partum,</hi> a years bird, or a <hi>childe of two years breeding,</hi> one whereof is ſpent in the <hi>conception,</hi> another in <hi>faſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the members;</hi> and yet a meer <hi>Embrion</hi> when it is <hi>born,</hi> and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unfit for moſt Auditories perhaps before ſome <hi>great man,</hi> or to a <hi>refined auditory:</hi> the command of ſome ſpecial <hi>friend,</hi> may <hi>deliver</hi> him of it with applauſe, anſwerable to his expectation, which is all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence he looks for. For though <hi>Narciſſus</hi>-like, <hi>they dote upon</hi> their <hi>own ſhadows,</hi> and conceit of their <hi>Embrion-works,</hi> as the <hi>Crow</hi> of her <hi>birds,</hi> and <hi>ſing plaudits</hi> to their own brain, not only falling in love with theſe their conceptions, as <hi>Pigmalion fell in love with his Ivory Image;</hi> but expect that others ſhould commend, and admire them for rare and excellent, as though they were found in the <hi>Phenix neſt:</hi> Yet ſo reaſonable are they, that the <hi>peoples acclamation</hi> ſatisfies them to the full. For like the <hi>Camelion,</hi> or the <hi>beaſt Ignarus,</hi> they can live by the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ire</hi> of mens <hi>praiſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:170108:7"/>
               <p> And to ſpeak rightly, the <hi>work</hi> and the <hi>wages</hi> are very proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. For proof whereof, I will inſtance another caſe, of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Not to tell you of him that <hi>dined</hi> with the <hi>ſmell</hi> of a <hi>cooks meat,</hi> and <hi>paid</hi> him upon demand, with the <hi>ſound of his money:</hi> when a <hi>Jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> by his ſubtile ſleight, threw <hi>millet-ſeed</hi> a great way, thorough the <hi>eye of a needle,</hi> and hoped to have ſome great reward; <hi>Alexander</hi> making no reckoning thereof, commanded one to give him a <hi>buſhel of thoſe ſeed,</hi> to practiſe his feats withal, and to keep his hand in ure. And methinks when theſe Miniſters thus offer, and intrude themſelves; they are ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently <hi>rewarded,</hi> when they are <hi>accepted:</hi> though oftentimes they fall ſhort of this: for as that <hi>Prentice</hi> of <hi>Apelles,</hi> in coveting to <hi>mend the noſe, marred the face:</hi> or as <hi>Seriphus</hi> the <hi>old drudge</hi> in <hi>Naples,</hi> by coveting to <hi>mend his blear'd eye, put it out:</hi> or as the <hi>fooliſh Dyer</hi> never thinks his <hi>cloth black</hi> enough, until it be <hi>burned:</hi> ſo theſe men many times, covet ſo much to <hi>gild,</hi> and ſet more <hi>lustre</hi> on their Sermons, that they make themſelves ridiculous by it. It faring with them, as it did with <hi>Neanthus,</hi> who having got <hi>Orpheus</hi> his <hi>harp,</hi> ſo <hi>jangled</hi> and jarred with it: that whiles he looked for <hi>listning beasts,</hi> and <hi>dancing trees,</hi> he brought the <hi>dogs</hi> about his <hi>ears.</hi> So that ſometimes, the <hi>leſſe laboured</hi> peeces are <hi>beſt accepted;</hi> yea, accepted of by the beſt. For its poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſome one or two of their Pocket Sermons, may be both <hi>honest and profitable;</hi> and then he hath great thanks, and is anſwerably accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated: As it fared with <hi>Cherilus a fooliſh Poet,</hi> who of a great number of <hi>Verſes,</hi> made <hi>ſeven good;</hi> for which he had <hi>ſeven peeces of gold;</hi> but for every other <hi>a buffet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for their other Sermons, be they never ſo accurately ſtudyed, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much gilt over with flouriſhes, and querks, when they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, and want matter of ſolid divinity; having more <hi>ſhew</hi> than <hi>force,</hi> and more <hi>ornament</hi> than <hi>fruit:</hi> However <hi>themſelves</hi> think of them, and <hi>others</hi> are taken with them, (ſuch hearers reſembling that <hi>young ſcholar</hi> in <hi>Athens,</hi> who went to hear <hi>Demoſthenes eloquence</hi> at <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> and was entangled with <hi>Layis's beauty:</hi> (As ever the <hi>light-headed,</hi> are <hi>light-heeled,</hi> ſuch <hi>Dina's</hi> will not eſcape <hi>deflouring</hi>) Yet the more ſolid and judicious know; that a <hi>Miniſter</hi> with a <hi>female wit,</hi> is the <hi>worst Hermaphradite;</hi> and that theſe are no more like Sermons, than a <hi>Briſtol stone</hi> is like a <hi>Diamond.</hi> And certainly thoſe have but <hi>ſenſual mindes,</hi> that admire them, and but poor <hi>hunger-ſtarved ſouls,</hi> that are ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 6.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Objection.</hi> You ſeem to condemn all <hi>ſecular learning</hi> in Sermons, and to reſtrain, or at leaſt to limit the <hi>gifts of the holy Ghoſt</hi> which are <hi>ſundry,</hi> and various, 1 Cor. 12.11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Far be it from finding room in my very thoughts: for certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as <hi>Solomon</hi> in <hi>building the temple,</hi> made moſt excellent uſe of <hi>Hiram</hi> and the <hi>Sidonians,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.14, 16. and as the <hi>Egyptians ſpoils</hi> ſerved
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170108:8"/>to adorn the <hi>Tabernacle:</hi> ſo the <hi>wiſdome</hi> and <hi>learning,</hi> all lawful <hi>arts,</hi> and the true <hi>ſayings of the very Heathen,</hi> may be of excellent uſe to him that would <hi>divide the word of God aright,</hi> and juſtly improve them to the honour of the giver. Yea, it grieves me not a little, when I ſee ſo excellent a thing as Divinity is, fall into a ſluttiſh handling. I ſee no reaſon, that ſo high a <hi>Princeſſe,</hi> ſhould be preſented to the <hi>people,</hi> in a <hi>ſordid dreſſe:</hi> Nor that he which <hi>ſpeaks</hi> from the <hi>Father of Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> ſhould deliver his <hi>embaſſage</hi> in an <hi>ill one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And I cannot but marvel, that any ſhould dare to uſurp the <hi>Chair of Paul;</hi> that were never brought up at the <hi>feet of Gamaliel.</hi> Or, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to aſcend the <hi>Pulpet,</hi> without <hi>ſtudy;</hi> taking more pains there, than they have done in their <hi>Library.</hi> And could heartily wiſh, they would either <hi>ſtudy more,</hi> or <hi>ſpeak leſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſpeak not for ruſticity, I know <hi>a good garment</hi> may be <hi>ſpoiled in the making.</hi> Nor do I think it a good ſpirit, that perſwades men to <hi>preach extempore;</hi> looking for <hi>divine ſupply,</hi> in the <hi>neglect of means.</hi> True, <hi>God</hi> is able to inſpire a man with tranſcendent abilities; but he will not do all that he can do: he can give an <hi>Harveſt without ſowing,</hi> as he did the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> in the <hi>year of Jubilee;</hi> but he will not. He could give <hi>light without the Sun,</hi> as in the <hi>Creation;</hi> but he will not: So he could give us <hi>wiſdome,</hi> and <hi>learning,</hi> without <hi>ſtudy,</hi> as to <hi>Solomon</hi> he once did; but he will not.</p>
               <p>Indeed the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> were <hi>rare Preachers;</hi> and yet but <hi>raw ſcholars:</hi> but withal, we may take notice, that they had a <hi>ſupply</hi> for this <hi>defect:</hi> they were immediately <hi>inſpired</hi> by the <hi>holy Ghost;</hi> yea, they were <hi>first Christs ſcholars,</hi> before they became <hi>the worlds tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, Mark</hi> 9.31. <hi>Luke</hi> 11.2. And therefore we ought to have the <hi>more preparation,</hi> by how much we have the <hi>leſſe revelation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor would I have all men tyed to one form of Preaching; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that every man would apply himſelf that way, wherein he is likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to <hi>excel, in edifying the Church of God;</hi> as commonly each Miniſter excels another ſome way. One excelleth for <hi>force of ſpeech,</hi> another for ſound and <hi>ſolid arguments;</hi> a third, for <hi>ſhaming of vice;</hi> a fourth, for <hi>perſwaſions;</hi> a fifth, is <hi>excellent</hi> for <hi>expounding the words;</hi> a ſixth, ſurpaſſeth in <hi>delivering the matter;</hi> a ſeventh, is happy for <hi>eaſes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience;</hi> an eighth, exquiſite in <hi>determining of ſchool-doubts.</hi> In a word, ſome are judicious to <hi>inform the underſtanding;</hi> others <hi>powerful</hi> to work upon the <hi>will</hi> and <hi>affections,</hi> and <hi>ſpeak</hi> home to the <hi>conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We admire <hi>profound Auſtin,</hi> for queſtions; <hi>learned Jerome,</hi> for expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions; <hi>pathetical Chryſoſtome,</hi> for amplifications; <hi>holy Bernard,</hi> for me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations; <hi>pithy Cyprian,</hi> for perſwaſions; <hi>ſweet Ambroſe,</hi> for alluſions; <hi>eloquent Nazianzen,</hi> for moving the affections, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But what is all this to theſe <hi>Athenian Preachers?</hi> It is one thing to <hi>ſalute Athens,</hi> in our way to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did; and another to <hi>ſtay there,</hi> and go no farther: one thing to uſe <hi>ſecular learning</hi> in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170108:8"/>Sermons ſparingly; I mean to ſprinkle here and there a <hi>ſentence, exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> or <hi>hiſtory,</hi> for <hi>ornament,</hi> and <hi>illuſtration;</hi> and another thing to crowd them ſo full of theſe, that no room can be afforded for <hi>Scripture.</hi> One thing to uſe <hi>flowers</hi> as <hi>men</hi> do, only for <hi>ſight</hi> and <hi>ſent;</hi> and another as <hi>Bees</hi> for <hi>honey</hi> and <hi>wax:</hi> not to <hi>gild their wings</hi> as <hi>butter-flies,</hi> but to <hi>fill their combs,</hi> and <hi>feed their young.</hi> Borrow theſe <hi>Jewels of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then</hi> you may, but make not a <hi>Calf thereof,</hi> to <hi>worſhip</hi> and <hi>adore:</hi> the which you do in rejecting to preach the words of eternal life, that you may vent theſe, together with your own frothy conceits, and fantaſtical flaſhes of wit. And may it not be ſaid of your <hi>Sermons,</hi> as one ſpake of a poor <hi>Apothecaries ſhop?</hi> that he could finde no <hi>drugs</hi> therein, for <hi>pots</hi> and <hi>boxes:</hi> Are not your hearers ſerved like <hi>Jacob,</hi> who when he looked for <hi>Joſeph,</hi> found nothing but his <hi>party-coloured coat?</hi> Are ye not like the <hi>Papists?</hi> who neglect the Bible, which is the <hi>Tree of Life,</hi> the <hi>Word of Life,</hi> the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Water of Life,</hi> to feed the peoples <hi>eyes</hi> with <hi>pictures</hi> and <hi>bawbles,</hi> and their <hi>ears</hi> with <hi>legends</hi> and <hi>fables.</hi> Are not your Sermons rather taken out of <hi>Platoes Academy,</hi> than out of <hi>Chriſts ſchool?</hi> Do you not curſedly prefer the <hi>Ethicks of Aristotle,</hi> the <hi>Odes of Pindar,</hi> the <hi>Morals of Plutarch,</hi> and other books of humane Learning, before <hi>divine testimonies?</hi> As the <hi>Pſalms of David,</hi> the <hi>Gospel of Christ,</hi> and the <hi>Epistles of Saint Paul. Much</hi> like the <hi>Council of Trent;</hi> who preferred <hi>unwritten Traditions of men,</hi> before the <hi>written Word of God:</hi> which is all one in effect, as if a man ſhould caſt away his <hi>fleſhy arm,</hi> or <hi>leg,</hi> and ſet on another of <hi>wood.</hi> For what is all humane learning, compared with Gods Word? but like a <hi>carcaſſe</hi> without the <hi>ſoul;</hi> or a meer <hi>image</hi> which ſeems fair, but being lookt into, is found <hi>earth.</hi> Yea, is not this as great a ſleighting of <hi>the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture?</hi> as for the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ope,</hi> in the <hi>firſt ſeſſion of the last council of Lateran,</hi> to <hi>lay</hi> them at his <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It were honour ſufficient, to admit <hi>humane learning,</hi> and all lawful <hi>Arts,</hi> as <hi>ſo many ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s of honour, to attend this Queen of Heaven-Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity:</hi> it is abominable, to make her ſubſervient to them: he is an ill <hi>hoſt,</hi> not worthy the name <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> who ſo ſuffers his <hi>Inne</hi> to be taken up by <hi>ſtrangers,</hi> that there is not place enough for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither is it more <hi>profane,</hi> than it is <hi>ridiculous,</hi> in preaching to uſe a flouriſhing, and <hi>meretricious eloquence,</hi> puft up with unprofitable <hi>querks, fictions,</hi> and <hi>flaſhes of wit:</hi> God affects not <hi>Auliciſmes,</hi> and Courtly terms. Wit I love well, but I loath and abhor to hear light, gariſh, gawdy, and meretricious painting in Sermons; Flaſhes of wit, and playing upon a Text: which was wont to be the guiſe and manner of our <hi>Court</hi> or <hi>Trencher-Chaplains:</hi> And wherein the <hi>Rean of their honour,</hi> and pride lay: Becauſe this would more become, or befit a <hi>Tavern,</hi> than the Majeſty of a <hi>Temple.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor do I think it any grace, for <hi>Ministers</hi> in their Preaching, to <hi>come
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170108:9"/>with the enticing words of mans wiſdome;</hi> and the rarities of humane e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence: <hi>but in the evidence and demonſtration of the Spirit, and of power,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.1, to 14. &amp; 1.17, 18. <hi>Chriſt taught the people with au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority:</hi> gravity becomes the Pulpet.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 7.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But thy Sermons are only ſtuft with Authorities from the <hi>Ancient Fathers, Philoſophers,</hi> &amp;c. and what more commendable, than ſweet and ſententious ſayings?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Suppoſe it be ſo, yet <hi>proverbs</hi> are for <hi>ornament,</hi> not for the <hi>whole ſtuff; pearls</hi> grace a <hi>garment,</hi> but it were a ſtrange garment made of nothing but <hi>pearls;</hi> much like a <hi>body</hi> made all of <hi>bones,</hi> without <hi>nerves, ſinews, ligaments, fleſh,</hi> and <hi>skin;</hi> moſt ugly to behold. <hi>We will make thee borders of gold, with ſtuds of ſilver,</hi> Cant. 1.11. ſtuds, and borders, the <hi>veſture</hi> it ſelf is made of another peece. <hi>The words of the wiſe are as nails,</hi> Eccleſ. 12.11. and nails finiſh the building, other materials went before.</p>
               <p>Indeed when <hi>proverbs</hi> are uſed as ornaments, <hi>Summes,</hi> and <hi>corollaries, brief and happy concluſions,</hi> they both leave a <hi>deeper impreſſion</hi> in the <hi>heart,</hi> and take a <hi>ſtronger hold</hi> on the <hi>head.</hi> And this is to turn the <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of humane knowledge, into <hi>wine;</hi> whereas they turn all our <hi>wine</hi> into <hi>water:</hi> and are ſo wedded to the <hi>Muſes,</hi> that they are enemies to the <hi>Graces.</hi> For they ſo deprive us of the food of life, the Scripture; (without which never any ſoul was converted, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 19.7.) that the <hi>ſenſe</hi> may <hi>glut</hi> it ſelf, on their <hi>curious-pencill'd peeces,</hi> while the ſpectatour ſhall be even <hi>chap-fallen,</hi> for want of <hi>victuals.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor can they pretend the leaſt reaſon for their ſo doing: ſave <hi>Satans gain,</hi> and their <hi>own glory:</hi> For,</p>
               <p>Firſt, as it is more <hi>painful,</hi> to caſt forth ones <hi>empty hand,</hi> than if it be <hi>poiſed</hi> with ſome ſtone, or other matter of <hi>weight:</hi> ſo it is more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome to them, and they take greater pains, in contriving theſe <hi>fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and uſeleſſe Sermons,</hi> that have in them nothing of moment; than others do, who preach <hi>ſerious</hi> and ſolid Divinity, which converts the ſoul, and makes a new creature.</p>
               <p>Secondly, they have no need to ſeek farther; <hi>the Scriptures</hi> are ſo full and compleat: <hi>It is able to make a man wiſe to ſalvation, and perfect unto all good works; it is given by inspiration from God, and is profitable for doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for instruction,</hi> &amp;c. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15, 16, 17. Yea, the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> to make it more amiable, hath given it theſe <hi>titles,</hi> viz. <hi>a lanthorn,</hi> to direct us; <hi>a medicine,</hi> to heal us; <hi>a guide,</hi> to conduct us; <hi>a bit,</hi> to reſtrain us; <hi>a ſword,</hi> to <hi>defend</hi> us; <hi>water,</hi> to waſh us; <hi>fire,</hi> to inflame us; <hi>ſalt,</hi> to ſeaſon us; <hi>milk,</hi> to nouriſh us; <hi>wine,</hi> to rejoyce us; <hi>rain,</hi> to refreſh us; <hi>a treaſure,</hi> to enrich us, and the <hi>key</hi> to unlock heaven-gates unto us: ſo <hi>naming the word all things,</hi> that we might only deſire it, inſtead of all things.</p>
               <p>Men talk much of the <hi>Philoſophers ſtone,</hi> that it turneth <hi>copper</hi> into
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170108:9"/>
                  <hi>panaces</hi> the <hi>herb,</hi> that it is good for all diſeaſes; of <hi>catholicon</hi> the <hi>drug,</hi> that it is inſtead of all purges; of <hi>Vulcans armour,</hi> that it was an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of proof againſt all thruſts and blowes, and other the like: but whatſoever they did vainly attribute to theſe things, for bodily good, we may with full meaſure, aſcribe juſtly to the Scripture for ſpiritual. <hi>Auguſtine, Tanta facta ſunt quanta tunc fieri debuerunt, tanta ſcripta ſunt quanta nunc legi debuerunt, His ſalubriter &amp; parva corriguntur, &amp; parva nutriuntur, &amp; magca oblectantur ingenia. Nay,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Scriptures are ſo fit and full, Ut in eis quotidie proficerem, ſic eas ſolas ab ineunte pue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritia uſque ad decrepitam ſenectutem maximo otio, ſummo ſtudio, meliore ingenio conarer addiſcere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, their flocks (if they be wiſe, and godly) <hi>as new-born babes deſire only</hi> to be fed with <hi>the ſincere milk of the Word,</hi> contained in the <hi>Old,</hi> and <hi>New Testament;</hi> which are the <hi>two Brests</hi> of the <hi>Church, that they may grow thereby,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.2.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>God</hi> abhors that his <hi>ſeeds-men</hi> the <hi>Ministers,</hi> (and ſo they pretend themſelves to be) ſhould ſowe any thing, but the <hi>immortal ſeed of his Word, Mat.</hi> 13.19. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.9. which makes him ſo often complain againſt thoſe falſe prophets, who <hi>ran when he never ſent them; and ſpake out of their own hearts, and not from the mouth of the Lord,</hi> Jer. 23. his words are, <hi>He that hath my word, let him speak my word faithfully; what is the chaff to the wheat? is not my word like a a fire, ſaith the Lord, and like an hammer? that breaketh the rook in pieces,</hi> ver. 16.28, 29. which words ſpeak home to them, if they had but the grace to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it. But let them hear the <hi>Apoſtle, The weapons of our warfare,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, are not carnal, but mighty through God, to the pulling down of ſtrong holds; caſting down imaginations, and every high thing that exalteth it ſelf against the knowledge of God, and bringing into captivity every thought to the obedience of Christ,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.4, 5.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 8.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gods word</hi> may be compared to a <hi>Cannon</hi> with <hi>bullets;</hi> whereas wit and <hi>humane eloquence,</hi> is but like <hi>a Piece charged</hi> only <hi>with powder;</hi> which may make a great noiſe, but throweth not down ſin. <hi>The word of God is quick, and powerful, and ſharper than any two-edged ſword, piercing even to the dividing aſunder of ſoul and spirit, and of the joynts and the marrow; and is a diſcerner of the thoughts, and intentions of the heart,</hi> Heb. 4.12. whence it is, the Apoſtle ſo frequently oppoſeth his Preaching, to theſe <hi>Verbaliſts;</hi> who preach themſelves, and not <hi>Chriſt; that deliver not the word of God,</hi> but <hi>Poetry, Roman History,</hi> the ſayings of <hi>Orators, Philoſophers,</hi> &amp;c. Ile give you two or three inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of many, I wiſh they would minde his words: <hi>We preach not our ſelves,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>but Chriſt Jeſus the Lord; neither do we handle the Word of God deceitfully,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.2, 5. <hi>nor have we ſhunned to declare unto you the whole counſel of God,</hi> Act. 20.27. and again, <hi>When I came unto you, bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, my speech, and my preaching, was not with enticing words of mans
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170108:10"/>wiſdome; but in demonſtration of the spirit, and of power, that your faith ſhould not ſtand in the wiſdome of men, but in the power of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.4. and again, <hi>In declaring unto you the testimony of God; I determined not to know any thing among you, ſave Jeſus Chriſt and him crucified: which things alſo we speak, not in the words which mans wiſdome teacheth, but which the holy Ghoſt teacheth, comparing ſpiritual things with spiritual,</hi> ver. 2, 13. and again, <hi>Chriſt ſent me to preach the Gospel; not with the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of words, leſt the croſſe of Christ ſhould be made of none effect,</hi> chap. 1.17. and laſtly, <hi>I am not aſhamed of the Gospel of Christ; for it is the power of God unto ſalvation, to every one that beleeveth,</hi> Rom. 1.16.</p>
               <p>But how contrary to the <hi>Apostle</hi> are theſe men in every thing? They preach themſelves, and not Chriſt; they deliver not the Word of God, but Poetry, Roman Hiſtory, the ſayings of <hi>Orators, Philoſophers,</hi> &amp;c. not in the demonſtration of the Spirit, and of power, but with the enticing words of mans wiſdome, and the rarities of humane eloquence. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was not aſhamed of that preaching which the world counted fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhneſs, 1 Cor. 1.18, 21, 23. But theſe are, yea they dare not make uſe of <hi>Moſes,</hi> or the <hi>Prophets,</hi> or the <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> or the ſame Saint <hi>Paul</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermuch: leſt it ſhould be thought, they have <hi>more grace</hi> than <hi>wit,</hi> and <hi>leſſe learning</hi> than <hi>religion.</hi> They ſtrive ſo to be accounted great Scholars, and curious Preachers, that they are <hi>aſhamed of the Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> and ſcorn to deliver things ſo common, counting ſuch plain prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, no better than fooliſhneſs, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.18. though <hi>God</hi> calls their witty Preaching fooliſhneſs, and is pleaſed by that Preaching which they ſo ſleight, to ſave them that are ſaved, <hi>verſe</hi> 18, to 30.</p>
               <p>But your <hi>fine wits,</hi> who prefer <hi>their ſins</hi> before <hi>their ſouls,</hi> care not for ſuch courſe ſtuff, neither can theſe <hi>Amnons</hi> of the people, eat other <hi>cakes,</hi> then ſuch as are of <hi>Tamars baking.</hi> And therefore they ſwarm to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, to hear an eloquent Rhetorical Preacher, as thoſe <hi>Idolaters</hi> did, to the <hi>houſe of Baal,</hi> 2 Kings 18. <hi>as where the dead carcaſſe is, thither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the Eagles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It hath been uſual for ſuch as come in their <hi>own names,</hi> to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and entertained with general applauſe; while they that come in <hi>Chriſts name,</hi> have been ſleighted, if not perſecuted. <hi>Mahomet</hi> and the <hi>Pope,</hi> poſſeſs three parts of the world: whereas they that beleeve the <hi>Gospel,</hi> are few in number, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.16. <hi>Michaia</hi> delivers the <hi>truth, Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dekiah</hi> ſpeaks <hi>falſly:</hi> yet <hi>Zedekiah</hi> is credited, and preferred to the <hi>Kings</hi> Table, while <hi>Michaia</hi> is laid by the heels, and ſed with the bread of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, and the water of affliction, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.6, 12, 13, 14. Among the <hi>Jews, Baal had four hundred and fifty falſe prophets,</hi> maintained ſumptuouſly: <hi>God but one</hi> true Prophet, and he was forced to hide his head, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.22. <hi>Our Saviour</hi> was entertained by ſome few, but his oppoſers the <hi>Prieſts and Phariſees,</hi> were adored of all, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.22. though indeed their refuſal of him, more ſtrongly approved him; <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gold;</hi> of <hi>Cornucopia,</hi> that it hath all things neceſſary for food in it; of <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:170108:10"/>ther could he be proved the Meſſias, if they had not rejected him. <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> could have no audience: the truth muſt not be heard; but all of all ſorts, cry out for <hi>Diana,</hi> Acts. 19.34. Yea, <hi>aul</hi> complains, that all they which were in <hi>Aſia,</hi> turned from him, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. and the <hi>chief Jews</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> tell him, that his <hi>Sest is every where spoken against,</hi> Acts 28.22. Yea, <hi>Simon Magus</hi> had ſo bewitched the people, that they all took him, <hi>for the great power of God:</hi> even a <hi>Sorcerer,</hi> ſhall have more diſciples, and applauders, than an <hi>Apoſtle;</hi> Acts 8.10. How then ſhould not theſe ſilver-tongued Preachers; that only ſtudy to pleaſe the ear, and ſpeak well, not be more applauded, than thoſe that deliver the plain truth? which makes men become their enemies, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.16. Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when their hearers relliſh no Preaching, except it be full fraught with ſecular learning, and flaſhes of wit. For ſuch as the <hi>paſtor</hi> is, ſuch are the <hi>people: Like Shepherd, like ſheep,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeaks, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4.9.</p>
               <p>Neither go they to Church to any other end, but as ſome <hi>Heirs</hi> goe to the <hi>Univerſities,</hi> and <hi>Innes of Court:</hi> not to get <hi>learning, law,</hi> or <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> but to learn <hi>faſhion,</hi> and <hi>complement;</hi> being like Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> before his converſion, who took great delight in hearing Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> but it was more for the <hi>eloquence</hi> of the words, than for the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of the matter: Yea, as himſelf confeſs'd after repentance, being a young man, he ſo affected eloquence, that in vain things he heard <hi>Jupiter thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and therewithal committed adultery, <hi>Confeſſion</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>As ignorant <hi>Lapidaries</hi> chuſe <hi>ſtones</hi> that delight the <hi>eye,</hi> and meaſure the <hi>value</hi> not by the <hi>hidden virtue</hi> of them, but by the <hi>outward glister<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> ſo theſe prefer ſuch Sermons, as pleaſe the ſenſe, before others which work upon the affections, and change the heart: they are like lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>children,</hi> who if they ſee a <hi>Corn-field</hi> over-grown with <hi>poppies,</hi> (a fit reſemblance of ſuch a Sermon) think it very glorious, and prefer it exceedingly before other <hi>Corn,</hi> that is <hi>cleer from weeds.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 9.</head>
               <p>But to let paſs the invalidity of their judgements, I would fain know what they are the better, for theſe rare, Rhetorical Sermons? Doth it not fare with them, as it did with <hi>Ezekiels</hi> Auditors? who took ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in his Preaching, that <hi>he was unto them, as the pleaſant voice of a Muſitian:</hi> and they commended him highly, but <hi>yet their hearts ran after their covetouſneſs;</hi> as did <hi>Herods</hi> after his <hi>inceſt,</hi> for all he <hi>delighted</hi> ſo much <hi>in</hi> Johns <hi>Preaching,</hi> Ezek. 33.31, 32.</p>
               <p>You ſhall hear them highly commend theſe Sermons: <hi>Oh it was a rare Sermon! He is an excellent man! It was the best Sermon that ever</hi> I <hi>heard! He is an admirable Preacher,</hi> &amp;c. But ask them what they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member of ſuch a Sermon, and you ſhall finde (admit the Sermon be Indifferently mix'd with <hi>pleaſant</hi> and <hi>profitable things</hi>) that ſuch an one; like a <hi>crack'd veſſel, poureth out of his</hi> thoughts <hi>all the good liquor,</hi> and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170108:11"/>
                  <hi>keepeth only the dregs:</hi> His <hi>memory</hi> is not like the <hi>Sieve,</hi> or <hi>Cullender,</hi> which <hi>casteth out</hi> the <hi>chaff</hi> and <hi>water, retaining</hi> the <hi>good corn,</hi> and <hi>herbs;</hi> but like a <hi>Searce of Lawn,</hi> which <hi>keeps</hi> in the <hi>groſſe things,</hi> and lets the <hi>purer paſſe:</hi> Or,</p>
               <p>Secondly, ask them, what rare effects did it work within? What won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders wrought it in thee? What excellency, or what goodneſs haſt thou received, or gained by it? For that is to be accounted an excellent, a rare, &amp; a good Sermon, which produceth rare effects in thee, makes thee better than thou waſt before; and then maiſt thou wonder, when the Preacher worketh wonders in thy ſoul. A faithful Preacher, cares not ſo much for thy <hi>verbal</hi> commendations, as thy <hi>real.</hi> Thy good <hi>conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation,</hi> is his beſt <hi>commendation;</hi> his <hi>commending,</hi> ſtands in thine <hi>amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding;</hi> and thy godly <hi>practice,</hi> is his beſt <hi>praiſe.</hi> The <hi>ſheep</hi> that ſaith no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, commends her <hi>Shepherd,</hi> when her <hi>skin</hi> is whole, her <hi>fleece</hi> fair, and <hi>her ſelf</hi> in well-liking. Likewiſe he <hi>hears well,</hi> that <hi>doth well;</hi> he <hi>learns well,</hi> that <hi>lives well;</hi> and he only doth prove himſelf <hi>a good hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> which <hi>hears</hi> the <hi>truth</hi> in <hi>humility, beleeves</hi> it in <hi>ſimplicity,</hi> and <hi>obeys</hi> it with <hi>alacrity.</hi> A good inſtitution, changeth both <hi>judgement</hi> and <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners;</hi> as it fared with <hi>Polemon,</hi> a diſſolute young <hi>Grecian,</hi> who going one day to hear <hi>a Lecture of Xenocrates,</hi> not only marked the <hi>eloquence,</hi> and ſufficiency of the Reader, but brought home ſo apparent, and <hi>ſolid fruit</hi> thereof, that it cauſed <hi>a ſudden change, and amendment</hi> of his former <hi>life.</hi> Whereas theſe hearers, (mark what I ſay, and ſee whether I am miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken) like <hi>Pharaohs lean kine, feed much,</hi> but are <hi>never the fatter:</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps they have ſomewhat enriched their <hi>tongues,</hi> but their <hi>lives</hi> are not a whit changed: For what is their <hi>religion?</hi> to ſay the Creed is all their <hi>ſaith;</hi> to pay what they needs muſt, all their <hi>equity;</hi> to give fair words, all their <hi>bounty;</hi> to take their own, all their <hi>mercy;</hi> to carry a formal profeſſion, all their <hi>piety;</hi> to cry God mercy, all their <hi>penitence;</hi> and to come to Church, all their <hi>conſcience.</hi> Yea, hear they never ſo many of theſe Sermons, they can go as merrily away, with all kinde of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs at their heels, as <hi>horſes</hi> with an <hi>empty Coach.</hi> And when the truth of obedience, and power of godlineſs is wanting, I pray tell me what difference between an <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> and an <hi>Iſhmaelite?</hi> a <hi>circumciſed He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew,</hi> and an <hi>uncircumciſed Philistine?</hi> a <hi>baptized Engliſh man,</hi> and an <hi>unwaſhen Turk?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea, they are ſo far from being <hi>Christians,</hi> that they have not made one ſtep towards <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi> The firſt ſtep to <hi>Religion,</hi> is to <hi>love Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> in another: whereas theſe men generally <hi>hate, ſcoff</hi> at, and <hi>perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute</hi> the power of <hi>Religion,</hi> whereever they perceive it. Yea, they hate that <hi>Preaching,</hi> whereby alone men become <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> For let them hear a Miniſter, that preaches profitably, if they can find no fault with his Sermon, at leaſt their verdit ſhall be, Oh he is <hi>no Scholar:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as if their opinion be askt, touching any other, ſuppoſe him <hi>a dumb dog,</hi> that perhaps hath been tongue-tyed from his birth, (like <hi>Craſus his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170108:11"/>ſon</hi>) they will tell you he is <hi>a great ſcholar,</hi> a man of <hi>deep learning,</hi> and great knowledge; though he want utterance, and cannot expreſs himſelf, nor <hi>vent his knowledge:</hi> when the plain truth is, he hath <hi>no knowledge to vent;</hi> only theſe men love to <hi>justifie,</hi> what God in his Word <hi>condemns;</hi> and to <hi>condemn</hi> what he <hi>justifies,</hi> Luc. 16.15. for if men Preach fruitleſly, they are great ſcholars, though they ſhew it not: or, if they do, though theſe underſtand it not, as one ſpake of <hi>Quintilians Oratour,</hi> a learned man I warrant him, for I underſtood him never a word. Whereas let men Preach faithfully, and powerfully, though they ſhew never ſo much learning, they are no Scholars. I wiſh men would obſerve this deepneſs of Satan, to hinder the means of converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not be led like ſots, to <hi>hear all godly Preachers with prejudice,</hi> for you ſhall never hear them commend a wholeſome and profitable Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</p>
               <p>Yea, theſe <hi>Athenians</hi> (regarding <hi>delight,</hi> not <hi>profit</hi>) will ſcarce have their ears open for any thing but <hi>novelties;</hi> but will go neer to quarrel with the Preacher, if he tells them any thing they have heard before, and cenſure him for <hi>a dunce, of no reading, an empty Divine, without ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larſhip:</hi> adding thereto, that his <hi>ſpeech</hi> was rude, his <hi>voice</hi> low, his <hi>words</hi> ſtuck like burrs in his <hi>throat,</hi> he <hi>railed</hi> upon the <hi>Pariſh,</hi> ſpeaks daggers, and aimed at ſome body.</p>
               <p>Yea, if you will beleeve them, as they beleeve their Prophets, ſuch Sermons are not to be heard, for they drive men to deſpair. It is one of the many falſe doctrines they teach, reſembling herein the <hi>Papists,</hi> who <hi>magnifie their own,</hi> and <hi>vilifie the writings of God;</hi> ſaying, thoſe will make men <hi>good Catholicks,</hi> theſe will make them <hi>Hereticks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And no marvel, that rational men, ſhould beleeve ſuch horrible un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths, ſince <hi>the wiſdome of the fleſh is enmity against God,</hi> Rom. 8.7, 8. that is, more than barely <hi>an enemy.</hi> Again, <hi>they will not receive the truth in love, therefore are given up to beleeve lies,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.11.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 10.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Objection.</hi> You have ſhewn how theſe Preachers are not more <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by ſome,</hi> than they are <hi>condemned by others;</hi> but how ſhall the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by, <hi>viz.</hi> the indifferent Reader judge, whether of them is in the right.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> By their
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Deſcription</hi> of vices and graces.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Reſolving</hi> caſes of conſcience.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Viſiting</hi> of the ſick.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, they make a deſcription of our <hi>graces,</hi> and <hi>infirmities,</hi> even as <hi>a Town-cryer</hi> of <hi>things</hi> that are <hi>lost,</hi> who makes inquiry after <hi>an horſe, a dog,</hi> or the like; deſcribing his <hi>hair,</hi> his <hi>ſtature,</hi> his <hi>ears,</hi> with other <hi>marks</hi> and <hi>tokens:</hi> but bring either unto him, he knows them not. For like as one that ſits in his chair, can paint <hi>Seas, Rocks, Shelves,</hi> and <hi>Havens</hi> upon a board, and make the model of <hi>a tall Ship</hi> to <hi>ſail</hi> in all
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170108:12"/>ſafety; but put him to it in earneſt, he knows not <hi>what to do,</hi> nor <hi>where to begin.</hi> So fares it with theſe Divines; they can <hi>ſpeak of every thing by roat, know nothing</hi> cordially, and <hi>in experience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, in reſolving <hi>caſes of conſcience;</hi> let a poor diſtreſſed ſoul come unto theſe <hi>Verbalists,</hi> to be reſolved of his doubts, they are as fit to reſolve them, as the <hi>Sooth-ſayers</hi> were to interpret <hi>Nebuchadnezza s dream,</hi> which himſelf could not ſo much as remember; and as able to give advice, as the <hi>wiſe men of Egypt</hi> were to inſtruct <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> touching <hi>the famine</hi> to come, who could ſay juſt nothing, <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.8. or if they do, it is nothing but <hi>conceit,</hi> and <hi>melancholy:</hi> you muſt be <hi>chearful,</hi> avoid <hi>ſolitarineſs, drink a cup of wine,</hi> and the like. They can help to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, and <hi>cast us down;</hi> but what help is there in them, <hi>to raiſe us up?</hi> there they leave us in a forlorn condition, as the <hi>Priests</hi> left <hi>Judas,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his <hi>treaſon;</hi> or as the <hi>old Prophet of Bethel,</hi> left the <hi>Prophet of Judah,</hi> 1 Kings 13.22. wherein the caſe of their ſtock is much more miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, than was that of the <hi>Philistines,</hi> when they were in a quandary a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout keeping the <hi>Ark:</hi> for they asking counſel of their <hi>idolatrous Prieſts</hi> and Divines, were ſo far forth, and ſo well inſtructed, that thereby they were freed from a <hi>temporal judgement,</hi> 1 Sam. 6. but theſe as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks, are <hi>wels without water,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. they can afford no ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual refreſhment to the <hi>thirſty ſoul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, let one of theſe witty Preachers be ſent for, to <hi>viſit a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal man upon his death-bed,</hi> and to fit him for his departure, (as ſome being <hi>ſick,</hi> dare adventure to take Phyſick of an <hi>Horſe-leech</hi>) either he hath nothing to ſay, or nothing to the purpoſe: for as it is impoſſible to order the <hi>body</hi> aright, either in ſickneſs, or in health, without the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain knowledge of our <hi>complexion, age,</hi> and <hi>strength,</hi> and unleſs we mark in <hi>what parts</hi> it is moſt weak, or ſtrong; that accordingly choice may be made both of <hi>meats in health,</hi> and of <hi>remedies in ſickneſs:</hi> So concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſoul, whereas he can neither judge of a mans ſpiritual eſtate, nor apply a fit remedy; but like a <hi>ſilly Emperick, administers one and the ſame potion, to a burning Fever, and the cold Palſie; one plaiſter</hi> to <hi>an old iſſue,</hi> and a <hi>green wound:</hi> for you ſhall hear him tumble out the ſweet <hi>Promiſes</hi> of the Goſpel, without annexing the <hi>condition</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Repentance;</hi> or, if he name the condition, it ſhall be without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining the parties eſtate, or declaring what Repentance or Faith means. Though indeed if he ſhould do all this, I would fain know, what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort a diſtreſſed conſcience can receive from one, that although he talk of <hi>God, Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Hell,</hi> yet he ſeems to beleeve neither? as appears by his <hi>viciouſneſs,</hi> or <hi>lukewarmneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now are not theſe ſimple Divines, who think themſelves <hi>rare Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers,</hi> becauſe they are <hi>good Oratours?</hi> when the <hi>converſion of a ſoul</hi> is no other than <hi>a new Creation,</hi> who think with <hi>earthly balms,</hi> to cure the <hi>ſtroaks of Heaven;</hi> by the ſtrength of their own plots, to bind the hands of Omnipotency; and by the fineneſs of their little wits, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170108:12"/>the counſels of an infinite wiſdome. Well may they (like the <hi>Popingay,</hi> that braved it in her <hi>borrowed feathers,</hi> like the <hi>Aſſe,</hi> that jet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it in her <hi>Lions Skin,</hi> or like the <hi>Ape,</hi> that skipt up and down in her <hi>Maſters Jacket</hi>) be lifted up in their minds, and ſwoln with vaſt thoughts of themſelves: (for it is only an over-flowing conceit of their own abilities, which makes them to love whatſoever is theirs.) But others know them unworthy to ſpeak out of a Pulpet: for notwithſtanding their great flouriſh, yet their <hi>people periſh for want of knowledge;</hi> as if darkneſs be on the <hi>hill,</hi> what light is in the <hi>valley?</hi> Yea, they <hi>abound in ſwearing, and lying, and killing, and ſtealing, and committing adultery, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no knowledge of God in them,</hi> Hoſ. 4.1, 2. Well may they be great Scholars in humane learning, (as oftentimes the moſt effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>means</hi> are applyed to the <hi>ends</hi> leaſt to be deſired, which is a miſery) but they are dunces in divinity; at leaſt their underſtanding in experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Divinity, is <hi>as little</hi> as their preſumption <hi>is great.</hi> Deprive them of ſecular learning in a Sermon, or argument, and they are <hi>as weak as a Bull-ruſh.</hi> Yea, you put them to a <hi>non-plus,</hi> as <hi>Muncaſtor</hi> a famous <hi>School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter,</hi> did a <hi>Scholar</hi> of his at <hi>Greenwich,</hi> where he, and divers of the <hi>Queens Chaplains</hi> were at break-faſt; who being bid to crave a bleſſing upon the creatures, anſwered after much preſſing, that indeed he had <hi>a grace for dinner,</hi> and <hi>another for ſupper,</hi> but he had <hi>none for break-faſt.</hi> He which ſpeaks by <hi>roat,</hi> and not out of the abundance of his <hi>heart,</hi> is ſoon drawn dry.</p>
               <p>What compariſon then (even in the judgement of <hi>malice,</hi> and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of <hi>envy</hi> it ſelf) between theſe, and a ſolid Divine, whoſe <hi>heart</hi> is a <hi>Comment</hi> upon the whole <hi>Bible,</hi> and who hath the <hi>holy Ghoſt to teach him, even the deep things of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.10. They may think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves without compare, as thoſe <hi>ſhallow-headed Verbaliſts,</hi> Acts 17.18. to 22. under-valued Saint <hi>Paul;</hi> not thinking him worthy to carry their books after them for learning, becauſe he did not in like pompous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and with ſuch oftentation, ſet forth himſelf. But it was only in conceit, wherein alone pride conſiſteth. So how did thoſe <hi>Epicurian</hi> and <hi>Stoick Philoſophers</hi> ſcorn him, who in their learned and deep judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, was but <hi>a babler, and his preaching meer fooliſhneſs?</hi> Yea, what defences was Saint <hi>Paul</hi> driven to make for himſelf, about his plainneſs in unfolding the Goſpel? In like manner alſo did <hi>Corah, and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> (not for want of ignorance) compare themſelves with <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron.</hi> But a wiſer than they acquainteth us, that <hi>he who winneth ſouls is wiſe,</hi> Prov. 11.30. And that <hi>thoſe who by their teaching, turn many to righteouſneſs, ſhall ſhine as ſtars for ever and ever,</hi> Dan. 12.3. So that however <hi>Goliah</hi> may make <hi>the greater vaunts,</hi> yet <hi>David</hi> will prove the wiſer, and the better man.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Moon</hi> is <hi>glorious to a Candle,</hi> but <hi>pale to the Sun;</hi> the <hi>Lilly white</hi> to the <hi>wool,</hi> but <hi>Short</hi> of the <hi>Snow;</hi> and the <hi>ſwarthy</hi> compared with the <hi>Blackamer</hi> thinks himſelf <hi>fair:</hi> ſo theſe Preachers, theſe <hi>empty casks,</hi> theſe <hi>proud cox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combs,</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:170108:13"/>that have <hi>more wit than learning,</hi> and <hi>more learning than honeſty,</hi> or <hi>good intention,</hi> in the diſcharge of their Miniſtery, when they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare themſelves with ſuch as have <hi>neither wit, learning, honeſty, nor good intention,</hi> may think themſelves ſome-body; but if they compare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the meaneſt of Chriſts faithful Miniſters, they are not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to carry his Books after him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 11.</head>
               <p>And the reaſon of it may well be, their <hi>too good opinion of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves:</hi> being like <hi>Druſus, grand-father to Cato,</hi> who was very <hi>eloquent,</hi> and <hi>learned;</hi> but withal moſt <hi>ambitious</hi> and <hi>proud:</hi> For as in <hi>Luthers</hi> time, it was a Paradox, <hi>juſtitia cauſa injustitiae,</hi> a conceited <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> was the chief cauſe of all <hi>unrighteouſneſs:</hi> So may I ſay to theſe, <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia cauſa ſtultitiae,</hi> an opinion of <hi>wiſdome,</hi> is in a manner the ſole cauſe of all their <hi>ignorance,</hi> and <hi>folly.</hi> Many a man had proved wiſe, if he had not ſo thought himſelf: and commonly they are <hi>moſt proud,</hi> that have the <hi>leaſt cauſe.</hi> The more each <hi>earth</hi> advanceth it ſelf, they are ever the more <hi>barren.</hi> The fuller, and <hi>heavier ſcale,</hi> is ever <hi>loweſt;</hi> and the <hi>emptier</hi> the <hi>ear</hi> is of <hi>corn,</hi> the <hi>higher</hi> it ſtill <hi>perks up:</hi> So he that knoweth himſelf <hi>best, eſteemeth</hi> of himſelf <hi>leaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or, admit a man be like <hi>Atlas King of Mauritania,</hi> who for his great skil in the courſe of ſtars, is feign'd to <hi>hold up the firmament</hi> with his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, yet <hi>pride</hi> makes men <hi>decay in brain:</hi> for as when the <hi>Milt ſwelleth,</hi> all the reſt of the <hi>body waſteth:</hi> ſo as the <hi>heart ſwelleth,</hi> the <hi>brain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayeth:</hi> and which is the miſery, few proud wits are ever reformed. There was never <hi>holineſs,</hi> without <hi>humbleneſs;</hi> for <hi>God reſiſteth the proud, James</hi> 4.6. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.5. and as it is a ſign of the <hi>going down of the Sun,</hi> and of his <hi>departure,</hi> when our <hi>ſhadows</hi> grow <hi>long:</hi> ſo it is a ſign of <hi>the Spirits departure,</hi> when we entertain theſe <hi>high thoughts of our ſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, another reaſon of their ſtrange miſtake, in thinking ſo <hi>well of themſelves,</hi> ſo <hi>baſely of their betters,</hi> is, the generality of the people are extreamly taken, yea, tranſported with their ſingular faculty in Preaching, while thoſe Preachers whom I ſeem to magnifie, are as much neglected: Yea, not one in many, but will chuſe rather to hear them, than the other. Yea, who will not go from their own Paſtours, and paſs by many others, to hear one of their <hi>elaborate,</hi> and <hi>accurate peeces?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As this is the caſe, if they have a godly and powerful Miniſter in their own Pariſh, that will not let them <hi>ſleep,</hi> and <hi>ſnort</hi> in their ſins, but will <hi>rouze and raiſe</hi> them out of their <hi>ſecurity,</hi> and cry aloud a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their abominations; as God commands <hi>Ezekiel</hi> to do, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14 4. <hi>anſwer them according to their idols,</hi> preach to their neceſſities, preſſe them to holy duties, reprove them for their unholy practices, make known to them what evil conſciences they have, and how fearful their doom will
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170108:13"/>be, if they continue and go on in their wickedneſs, and ignorance; not ſparing to <hi>utter the whole counſel of God;</hi> to the end they may <hi>ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repent, and be ſaved.</hi> Then they will hate him ever after, as <hi>Amos</hi> ſpeaks, chap. 5.10. And that moſt deadly, as <hi>Ahab hated Eliah, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chala, Heredias John Baptist, the Jews our Saviour,</hi> and the <hi>Galatians</hi> Paul, ſaying, <hi>Away with ſuch a fellow from the earth, for it is not meet that be should live,</hi> Acts 22.22. And not only turn their backs upon him, but be ready to kill him for his kindneſs; as appears by a world both of <hi>teſtimonies,</hi> and <hi>examples:</hi> for I think I may ſay, there is not a <hi>man of God,</hi> either <hi>Prophet</hi> or <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> mentioned in the Bible; no, not <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, that hath not been ſome way perſecuted, for delivering <hi>Gods errands</hi> to the people, and ſpeaking that <hi>truth,</hi> which if they had left one ſyllable unſpoken, they had been deſtroyed by God himſelf that gave them the charge: ſee <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.17. and 15.10.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Phariſees</hi> you know, could not endure <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> becauſe he came to break their <hi>cuſtomes,</hi> Luc. 6.2. The <hi>Maſters of the Pythoneſs,</hi> Acts 16.21. objected this againſt <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas, that they did teach cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes not lawful for them to receive.</hi> For this cauſe was that uproar at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> the copy-hold of <hi>Demetrius</hi> was touched, he and his fellows were hindred in their profits, &amp;c. Yea, the Jews in their blind zeal, were ſo furious and mercileſs, that they put <hi>Stephen</hi> to <hi>death,</hi> who ſought to bring them to eternal <hi>life;</hi> ſtoning him for a blaſphemer againſt <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Law;</hi> who was a man <hi>full of faith, and power, and of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> Acts 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gods</hi> truth, if you mark it, would cry down mens ſins, as Preaching would have done <hi>Demetrius's trade;</hi> and therefore no marvel if the <hi>tradeſmen</hi> of iniquity, are up in arms againſt the <hi>Gospel,</hi> as <hi>Demetrius</hi> was againſt <hi>Paul.</hi> And did not the <hi>Gospel croſs their ſins, they</hi> would not <hi>croſs the Gospel:</hi> But the <hi>waves</hi> do not <hi>beat</hi> or <hi>roar,</hi> any where ſo much, as at the <hi>bank</hi> that <hi>reſtrains</hi> them.</p>
               <p>While the Preacher walks in <hi>Generals,</hi> every man can be maſter of his own patience: but deſcending to <hi>particular application,</hi> as <hi>Nathan</hi> ſerved <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>John Herod,</hi> then let him look to himſelf. Or, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit he preaches unprofitably, as caring only to <hi>pleaſe,</hi> not to <hi>inform:</hi> or ſtands more upon his <hi>own credit,</hi> than the <hi>peoples benefit:</hi> ſo long they will hear the <hi>Word</hi> very orderly, and delight in it; (For none ſo bad, but he <hi>loves the light as it shines,</hi> but <hi>as it diſcovers, and directs they hate it</hi>) Whiles we <hi>ſearch</hi> no farther than their <hi>dead flesh,</hi> they can be <hi>quiet;</hi> but if we once touch them to the <hi>quick,</hi> we ſhall quickly hear of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 12.</head>
               <p>And the reaſons of their ſo doing, (among many others) are theſe three: Firſt, theſe <hi>Serpents</hi> will <hi>hiſs,</hi> if we <hi>trouble</hi> their <hi>nests</hi> never ſo little, becauſe they know themſelves <hi>guilty.</hi> It is a ſure ſign the <hi>horſe</hi> is <hi>galled,</hi> that <hi>ſtirs</hi> too much when he is touched, <hi>Num.</hi> 5.27. In the <hi>Law
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170108:14"/>of Jelouſies,</hi> if the <hi>ſuspected wife</hi> were <hi>guilty,</hi> that drank of the <hi>bitter waters</hi> of <hi>trial,</hi> ſhe would preſently <hi>ſwell:</hi> if otherwiſe, ſhe was well enough. <hi>Unſound flesh</hi> loves to be ſtroaked; the leaſt <hi>roughneſs</hi> puts them into a <hi>rage. Sore eyes</hi> cannot abide the <hi>light</hi> of the <hi>Sun.</hi> The naked truth, makes ſo little <hi>for,</hi> and ſo much <hi>against</hi> reſolute ſinners, that they will <hi>carp,</hi> and <hi>ſtorm,</hi> and <hi>fret,</hi> and <hi>chafe,</hi> and <hi>fume,</hi> and <hi>ſwell,</hi> and <hi>rage,</hi> and be ready to <hi>burſt</hi> again when they hear it. Inſtead of <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitence,</hi> they break out into <hi>choler; fury</hi> ſparkles in thoſe <hi>eyes,</hi> which ſhould guſh out with <hi>water:</hi> Like <hi>Gain, Ahab,</hi> and <hi>Herod,</hi> they are never troubled for their ſins, only they are vexed to hear of them. They are like the <hi>mad man,</hi> that <hi>wounded</hi> his <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> even while he was admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring <hi>Phyſick</hi> to him for his <hi>recovery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, the <hi>Word of God,</hi> is like ſome fructifying <hi>dew</hi> or <hi>rain,</hi> which <hi>falls</hi> not upon any <hi>ground</hi> in vain; but will either produce the <hi>herbs</hi> of good works, or the <hi>weeds</hi> of impiety: Every line of <hi>Gods Word,</hi> addes ſinew to the virtuous mind, and withal heals that vice which would be ſpringing in it. But as all <hi>bodies</hi> are not equally apt to be <hi>wrought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> by the ſame <hi>medicine:</hi> ſo are not all <hi>ſouls</hi> by the ſame <hi>means</hi> of grace. The ſame report wherewith the ſpirit of <hi>Rahab melts, hardens the King of Jericho,</hi> Joſhua 2. <hi>Sergius Paulus</hi> was <hi>converted, Elymas ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durated</hi> by the ſame Sermon, <hi>Acts</hi> 12. Therefore no wonder, if <hi>theſe spiders, thoſe bees,</hi> the <hi>wicked</hi> and the <hi>godly,</hi> ſuck the one <hi>honey,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>poiſon</hi> from the ſelf-ſame <hi>flower</hi> of holy Writ.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the <hi>Word of</hi> God is the <hi>rule</hi> of juſtice, which ſhews the <hi>crookedneſs</hi> of their ways. It is the <hi>Law,</hi> by which they ſhall be <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned,</hi> therefore they cannot endure it. They love not to have their <hi>conſciences awakened,</hi> but would <hi>ſleep quietly</hi> in their ſins; and he that deſires to <hi>ſleep,</hi> will have the <hi>curtains drawn,</hi> the <hi>light shut out,</hi> and <hi>no noiſe</hi> made. Beſides, they cannot hear the down-right <hi>truth,</hi> but they muſt alſo hear the <hi>ſentence</hi> of their own <hi>condemnation.</hi> It is the very <hi>word,</hi> by which they are <hi>judged</hi> and <hi>condemned:</hi> therefore they <hi>loath</hi> aſmuch <hi>to hear it,</hi> as a <hi>priſoner</hi> does abhor to hear his <hi>ſentence,</hi> from the <hi>juſt Judge.</hi> And indeed, if many love not to hear the worſt of their <hi>temporal cauſes,</hi> and <hi>caſes;</hi> nor yet of their <hi>bodily diſtempers,</hi> with which their <hi>lives,</hi> or <hi>eſtates</hi> be <hi>indangered;</hi> how much more will wicked men decline, from ſeeing their hainous <hi>abominations,</hi> and themſelves <hi>guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of <hi>bell,</hi> and eternal <hi>damnation.</hi> Though thereof there be an abſolute neceſſity, if ever they be ſaved.</p>
               <p>This is their main cauſe, or quarrel, againſt a zealous, and powerful Preacher; this above all makes them <hi>fret</hi> and <hi>ſtorm:</hi> But let <hi>envy ſweat, ſwell,</hi> and <hi>burſt,</hi> truth muſt be ſpoken: And indeed, why ſhould not Gods <hi>ſervants,</hi> take as free liberty in <hi>reproving,</hi> as the Devils <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi> take liberty in <hi>offending:</hi> Shall not the one be as <hi>bold for God,</hi> as the others are <hi>for Baal,</hi> and <hi>Beelzebub:</hi> Theſe are the reaſons, why they <hi>threat,</hi> when they ſhould (and others do) <hi>tremble;</hi> and <hi>jeer,</hi> when they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170108:14"/>ſhould <hi>fear;</hi> and <hi>mock</hi> when they ſhould <hi>mourn:</hi> like thoſe <hi>ſhameleſs,</hi> and <hi>graceleſs Iſraelites,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.10.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 13.</head>
               <p>Nor can the cauſe of wicked mens raging, bee imputed to any miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage in the meſſenger; for he may vindicate himſelf as <hi>Paul</hi> did, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. <hi>ver.</hi> 10. <hi>I have not ſpoken, but the Lord:</hi> and therefore as the <hi>Lord ſaid unto Saul, Act</hi> 9.4. that hee perſecuted him: ſo they which reſiſt any truth delivered out of the Word, do reſiſt <hi>God himſelf</hi> and not his <hi>meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger.</hi> And this for certain, if <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf were their Miniſter; and ſhould reprove them for their ſins, and denounce the judgments of <hi>God</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them for the ſame, as when he was upon the earth: not only the wit-founder'd <hi>drunkard,</hi> and <hi>prophane beaſt;</hi> but even <hi>civil honeſt men,</hi> and <hi>formal Chriſtians;</hi> would perſecute him to the death, as the <hi>Jews</hi> formerly did. Which is ſome comfort to a conſciencious Miniſter: Nor is it their ſhame to ſuffer, what <hi>Chriſt ſuffered;</hi> nor the others honour, to do as <hi>Judas</hi> and the reſt <hi>did,</hi> as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſpeaks. Neither can there bee a greater honour, done to a poor Miniſter than this: for as one of the <hi>Fathers</hi> hath it, it may well bee doubted, Miniſters open not the <hi>Word aright;</hi> when wicked men kick not againſt it. Yea, ſays <hi>Luther,</hi> to <hi>preach the Gospell</hi> as wee ought, is to ſtir up all the <hi>furies of Hell</hi> againſt us: and our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s <hi>Words Joh.</hi> 7.7. import no leſs, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.16.</p>
               <p>Now if this bee the caſe, no wonder they ſhould be for that preaching, which brings none of all this vexation: yea, they may hear one of their witty Rhetoricall preachers till <hi>dooms-day,</hi> and never bee <hi>diſturbed</hi> in their ſins, or <hi>diſquieted or moleſted</hi> in their conſciences, for it is not to her they ſpeak. Yea, ſuch preaching is rather an <hi>Antidote</hi> againſt what the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall preachers</hi> have averred, and does again <hi>cheer up</hi> their <hi>spirits,</hi> againſt all <hi>qualms of conſcience.</hi> As <hi>Davids harp</hi> cheered up <hi>Saul,</hi> when vexations and melancholly fits came upon him. Yea, the preaching of theſe brave Orators, and quaint wits; is to them as ſweet and melodious, as <hi>muſick:</hi> for which ſee <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.32. <hi>Micha</hi> 2.11. And this is the reaſon why moſt men walk in the <hi>broad way,</hi> and yet <hi>every man</hi> thinks to enter <hi>the ſtraight gate:</hi> The Devils Chaplains are chiefly heard, <hi>Chriſts Meſſengers</hi> are moſtly <hi>neglected.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A good and faithfull Miniſter, who is of Gods ſending, and ſtudies more to <hi>profit,</hi> then to <hi>pleaſe</hi> his <hi>people:</hi> that hee may the better <hi>undeceive the deceived,</hi> and (with bleſſing from above) <hi>pluck ſinners</hi> out of <hi>Satan</hi>'s <hi>ſnares:</hi> hee deals with his hearers, as the <hi>Prophet</hi> did by <hi>Hazaell;</hi> when hee plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly told him the abominable wickedneſs of his heart, even beyond belief: Or as <hi>Nathan</hi> did by <hi>David,</hi> when he ſo cunningly made him to pronounce ſentence againſt himſelf. Or as <hi>Jonah</hi> did by the <hi>Ninevites,</hi> when with his ſhort thundering ſermon, hee <hi>converted that great City.</hi> Or as <hi>Peter</hi> with his <hi>converts,</hi> when he told them they were the men, that had crucified the <hi>Son of God,</hi> the Lord of glory. Or as <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> did by <hi>Herod,</hi> and all that came unto him. Or <hi>as our Saviour</hi> by the <hi>woman of Samaria,</hi> when hee ſo repreſented the very <hi>thoughts of her heart</hi> to her <hi>conſcience;</hi> that ſhee was forced to confeſs, <hi>He hath told me all things that ever I did;</hi> which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170108:15"/>kind of preaching, they will never indure: becauſe they are reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>continue their ſins,</hi> and withall would <hi>preſerve the peace</hi> of their conſciences: which can never bee, ſo long as they hear the Word purely taught.</p>
               <p>Which yet they muſt do, if ever they bee ſaved: for there is no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſaved without <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Blood</hi> will never bee <hi>ſweet</hi> unto us, untill wee feel the <hi>ſmart</hi> of our <hi>ſins;</hi> and the neceſſity wee have of it. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men are <hi>convinced of their wickedneſs,</hi> they can no way bee <hi>capable of forgiveneſs:</hi> All men will grant, that <hi>without repentance</hi> there is <hi>no being ſaved:</hi> but what hope of their ſerious, and unfained repentance for ſin? who ſcarce know wherein they have offended. <hi>Sin</hi> muſt bee <hi>ſeen,</hi> before it can bee <hi>ſorrowed for:</hi> A man muſt bee <hi>ſick</hi> before hee will ſeek to the <hi>Phiſician,</hi> yea where is no <hi>diſcovery</hi> of the <hi>diſeaſe,</hi> the <hi>recovery</hi> of the <hi>health</hi> is in vain hoped for. Which makes <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſay, that it is as meer loſt labour, to preach unto a man the things of <hi>God,</hi> before hee bee hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with the ſight of his wants: as to offer light to a <hi>blind man,</hi> to <hi>ſpeak</hi> to a <hi>deaf man,</hi> or to labour to make a <hi>brute beaſt wiſe.</hi> But when our <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences</hi> are troubled, <hi>the Law</hi> having laid open our <hi>guiltineſs,</hi> and denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the deſerved <hi>puniſhment:</hi> this (and nothing but this) makes us run to <hi>Chriſt</hi> for remedy. <hi>Chriſt came to ſeek, and to ſave onely that which was loſt: the loſt ſheep of the houſe of Iſrael;</hi> even ſuch as utterly deſpair, in regard of all other helps, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.11. <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.10. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. God does not <hi>pour</hi> the <hi>oil of grace,</hi> but into a <hi>broken</hi> and <hi>contrite heart:</hi> and ſtill the <hi>deeper</hi> the ſence of <hi>miſery</hi> is, the <hi>ſweeter</hi> the ſence of <hi>mercy is.</hi> Nor can there bee a ſtronger argument, that a Miniſter ſtudies more to <hi>profit,</hi> then <hi>pleaſe</hi> men with his wholeſom counſell: as when hee will not let them <hi>ſleep</hi> and <hi>ſnort</hi> in their <hi>ſins;</hi> but cry aloud againſt their abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations. As well knowing, that it is better to looſe <hi>mens favours,</hi> then <hi>their ſouls:</hi> therefore hee will bee ſure to diſcharge his conſcience from the burthen of any ones blood.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section.</hi> 14.</head>
               <p>And ſo much to ſhew, how theſe witty preachers ſlight and ſcorn our ſolid divines, in regard of their excelling them (as they think) in learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and parts; &amp; how they are preferred by their hearers, with the reaſons of it? But wil you know withal, how they <hi>envie</hi> and <hi>maligne</hi> them, in reſpect of their ſucceſs and <hi>acceptance</hi> both with <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>good men.</hi> As if you obſerv it, Godly and conſciencious Miniſters, no leſs ſuffer from others of their own coat, then from their hearers. <hi>I</hi> mean from theſe men-pleaſers, as thus ſtands the caſe.</p>
               <p>A Godly Miniſter, that coms in <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>name;</hi> by his faithfull, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull preaching, and Gods bleſſing upon it: makes his hearers, of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall men to becom <hi>Christians, Act,</hi> 2.37. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.24, 25. Who may anſwer any that ſlight, and revile him, as that <hi>young man</hi> did the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> touching <hi>Jeſus, Joh.</hi> 9. <hi>Doubtleſs this is a marvelous thing, that yee do not know whence hee is, ſeeing he hath opened mine eyes, who was blind from my birth;</hi> inclined my <hi>will</hi> to obedience, which before was rebellions:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170108:15"/>ſoftned my <hi>heart,</hi> ſanctified, and quite changed my <hi>affections?</hi> ſo that I now <hi>love</hi> that good, which before I <hi>hated;</hi> and <hi>hate</hi> that <hi>evill</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I <hi>loved;</hi> and am delighted with thoſe holy exerciſes, which hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did moſt <hi>diſpleaſe mee,</hi> and am <hi>diſpleaſed</hi> with thoſe vain pleaſures and filthy ſins, which in times paſt did moſt <hi>delight mee;</hi> and therefore, <hi>if hee were not of God,</hi> and of his ſending, <hi>hee could have done no ſuch thing:</hi> if hee were not inſpired, and aſſiſted by his holy <hi>Spirit;</hi> and his preaching made effectuall, by the virtue and power thereof; hee could never have wrought in mee ſuch a <hi>change,</hi> and <hi>ſtrange alteration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as he converteth the good, ſo he convinceth the bad: and not ſeldom are ſuch ſo convinced, and the ſecrets of their hearts made ſo manifeſt, that their <hi>hearts</hi> even <hi>burn</hi> in their <hi>boſoms,</hi> and are ſo <hi>pricked,</hi> that they are ready to <hi>ſall down, and worſhip God, and report</hi> to their conſciences in private, <hi>that God is in ſuch</hi> a Miniſter, <hi>of a truth;</hi> as it fared with that <hi>unbelieving Iddiot,</hi> ſpoken of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.24.25. Thus does <hi>God</hi> give his faithfull <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> power to <hi>work miracles,</hi> as a ſeal to their Miniſtry; for converſion of ſinners is the onely miracle that the <hi>Goſpell</hi> now hath. But is ſuch, that <hi>Ceſars</hi> and <hi>Alexanders victories</hi> were nothing compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to this glorious conqueſt, which the Miniſters get in the hearts of men when they convert them. And this is it that ſo mads them, when they behold and conſider, how the people of <hi>God</hi> flock after their ſermons, affect and applaud their preaching, and how many of naturall men, become <hi>Chriſtians</hi> by hearing them: as wee may cleerly ſee, by what Saint <hi>John</hi> relates of their fellows, <hi>John</hi> 11.48. As mark well what is there ſet down! <hi>Then gathered the chief Priests and Phariſees a counſell, and ſaid; what do wee? for this man</hi> (meaning <hi>Chriſt</hi>) <hi>doth many miracles; if wee let him thus alone, all men will believe in him</hi> [obſerv the cauſe of their ſpite]. <hi>And from that day forth, they took counſell together for to put him to death, Joh.</hi> 11.47.48. And again, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12. <hi>The chief Prieſts conſulted that they might put Lazarus to death alſo, becauſe that for his ſake, or by reaſon of him, many of the Jews believed in Jeſus, verſe</hi> 10.11. Now as it fared with them, ſo fares it with theſe, they are vexed to ſee how <hi>God</hi> honours ſuch an ones Miniſtry, with the converſion of ſouls; and that his words are with ſuch power, that the people flock after him, as they were wont after <hi>Christ,</hi> while in the mean time, themſelvs are neglected and diſeſteemed: being as they ſuppoſe far greater ſcholars, and their ſermons more elaborate. For they will bee as long in the conception and breeding of them, as an <hi>Elephant</hi> is of her young; which being born, onely amazeth the hearers, and makes them at their wits end with admiration. <hi>Pride</hi> was ever <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious,</hi> and contumelious: thinking ſhee <hi>adds</hi> ſo much to her own repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, as ſhe <hi>detracts</hi> from others. And indeed the <hi>twinkling stars,</hi> at the approach of the <hi>Sun, loſe their light:</hi> and regain it nor, untill <hi>darkneſs</hi> bee upon the <hi>deep.</hi> Yea, the <hi>whiter</hi> the <hi>Swan</hi> is, the more <hi>black</hi> is the <hi>crow</hi> that's by her: They are not more <hi>propitious to vice,</hi> then they are <hi>malicious to virtue:</hi> for <hi>goodneſs</hi> alone, is the <hi>whetſtone</hi> of their <hi>malice,</hi> and makes them <hi>ſick</hi> of the <hi>splem, Prov.</hi> 29.27. Aman that hath no vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170108:16"/>himſelf, ever envies it in others. What is recorded of the <hi>Rulers and Governours of Babylon</hi> touching <hi>Daniel,</hi> is verified in theſe preachers, touching their fellow Miniſters: they therefore envie them, <hi>becauſe the Spirit is more excellent in them, and they can find no accuſation againſt them; unleſs it bee concerning the Law of their God, Dan.</hi> 6.3, 4, 5. I might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a cloud of examples of this nature; as <hi>Cains envying Abel, Eſau Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> the <hi>Patriarchs Joſeph, Saul David</hi> &amp;c. who were <hi>envied</hi> and <hi>hated,</hi> meerly for their <hi>goodneſs and virtue:</hi> but to what purpoſe? when every mans own heart can witneſs that of <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 29.27. to be true, <hi>A wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man is abomination to the juſt, and he that is upright in his way, is abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to the wicked.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section.</hi> 15.</head>
               <p>And ſo according to my promiſe, and as well as I can: I have given you the <hi>Character of a non-preaching Miniſter,</hi> of a witty and Rhetorical Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; And to the end you may bee <hi>inſtructed,</hi> aſwell by <hi>ſimilitude</hi> as <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety,</hi> I have declared the difference between theſe <hi>speculative Preachers,</hi> and <hi>experimentall Divines:</hi> whereby you may cleerly ſee, that the former in compariſon of the latter, is but a <hi>hollow Reed without pith:</hi> that though his <hi>memory</hi> bee ſufficiently <hi>ſull</hi> fraught, yet his <hi>judgment is hollow and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty:</hi> that hee is a <hi>barren</hi> divine, whoſe <hi>roots</hi> knowledge, bear no <hi>fruit</hi> but <hi>flowers:</hi> that for any ſolid divinity that is in him, hee may do as <hi>Pope Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtine</hi> the <hi>fifth</hi> did, who depoſed himſelf by reaſon of his ignorance. In a word, that ſuch a preacher is <hi>a bladder full of wind, a skin full of words, a fools-wonder, and a wiſe-mans fool.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the better to <hi>undeceive the deceived,</hi> and to the end that wee may bee gainers by this diſcovery: becauſe evill were as good <hi>not known,</hi> as <hi>not avoided.</hi> I will ſhew you how <hi>God's people are gulled,</hi> and <hi>Satan ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantaged</hi> by theſe non-preaching Miniſters. Who deal with the <hi>Church,</hi> as <hi>Vespatian</hi> did with <hi>Rome:</hi> who intending to <hi>invade</hi> the <hi>Empire,</hi> firſt made <hi>ſack of Alexandria,</hi> where were all the <hi>Granaries,</hi> that ſo hee might make them yield for want of <hi>victualls,</hi> and become his vaſſalls. As to <hi>way-lay an enemies proviſion,</hi> hath ever been held and ſound a principall <hi>ſtratagem in war.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>people</hi> are <hi>gulled,</hi> and Satan <hi>advantaged</hi> by this deep, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſh ſtratagem; I ſear few conſider as they ought: for if they did, they would as much <hi>deteſt</hi> theſe preachers, as now they <hi>applaud</hi> them. For what do they, but in a great meaſure (and aſmuch as in them lies), bring the heavieſt judgment upon the land that can befall any nation. Namely, a <hi>famine of the Word,</hi> and <hi>Gospel:</hi> Yea, they do not only bring this judgment upon thoſe pariſhes which they are placed in; but they draw thouſands from other pariſhes, (ſo hindering, and depriving their ſouls of their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall food): and make the wholeſom, and faithfull preaching of all good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and diſregarded by their people. Inſomuch, that they do the <hi>Devill ſervice,</hi> under a colour of <hi>ſerving Chriſt:</hi> and <hi>deſtroy ſouls,</hi> under a pretence of <hi>ſaving them.</hi> Nor is this their ſin of a narrow ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. For hereby the people me brought into ſuch a <hi>loathing</hi> of the true
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170108:16"/>
                  <hi>Mannah</hi> of <hi>Gods Word:</hi> that wee have juſt cauſe to fear our being depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of it. As what cauſe have wee to fear, the <hi>removall of our Candleſtick?</hi> and that <hi>God</hi> ſhould leave us in the <hi>dark,</hi> ſince moſt men (I fear ninety nine of an hundred) love <hi>darkneſs,</hi> rather then <hi>light;</hi> and had rather hear wit and froth, then the pure and ſolid Word of <hi>God.</hi> And to take away our faithfull Miniſters from us, when wee ſo little regard, and ſo ill and unworthily intreat and reward them, preferring the worlds preachers before thoſe who are of <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſending. <hi>Behold the days come ſaith the Lord God; that I will ſend a famine in the Land: Not a famine of bread, nor a thirſt of water; but of hearing the Word of the Lord,</hi> Amos 8.11.</p>
               <p>And this, (what ever carnall hearts conceive of it) were a greater judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then were the <hi>loſs of the Sun out of the firmament.</hi> Yea is it not juſt with <hi>God</hi> to take away the <hi>Lamp</hi> from that <hi>Nation?</hi> which hath (beſides all this) taken away the <hi>holy oil</hi> that ſhould maintain it; and to ſend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us a <hi>famine of preaching,</hi> who have brought <hi>a famine upon the Preachers:</hi> For do not moſt men deny them maintenance, unleſs by Law they are compell'd: and then if they give it, they as good as give their curſe with it. At leaſt they will ſmite him with the tongue, giving no heed to his words, as the <hi>Prophet Jeremiah</hi> complains, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.18. <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.45.46. And every penny they are forced to part with, is drawn from them, as ſo many drops of blood from the heart. Nor will they give it, but after ſuch a baſe manner; that one would ſcorn to accept of it: for then nothing but <hi>find faults</hi> or <hi>mock them:</hi> As, I like not his preaching, or he is a <hi>round-head,</hi> or I cannot edifie by his ſermons, or hee preaches the <hi>Law,</hi> and therefore is a railer: with an hundred the like, which apparently proves them <hi>God-haters,</hi> and <hi>Gospell-haters;</hi> as the <hi>root</hi> of this their enmity to the Miniſtry, is their <hi>enmity</hi> againſt <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Word,</hi> and <hi>holineſs:</hi> which they cannot indure, as appears by theſe places of Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.30. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.23, 24, 25. <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.9, 10, 11. <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.16. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. <hi>ver.</hi> 6. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.7. <hi>Num.</hi> 16.11. <hi>John</hi> 7.7. <hi>Act.</hi> 9.4.5.</p>
               <p>Wherefore look to it my brethren, leſt you rob your ſelvs, and your poſterity to the worlds end, of injoying this <hi>matchleſs mercy,</hi> this <hi>unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel'd pearl.</hi> And <hi>Lord</hi> I fear, that <hi>England</hi> ſhall want the <hi>Gospell!</hi> when the <hi>Barbarians receive it:</hi> becauſe <hi>England</hi> had the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> and did ſo little eſteem of it. You indeed ſet a low price upon it, and thereafter deal with the publiſhers of it; But O what large <hi>bribes</hi> would <hi>Satan</hi> give! (whoſe Chaplains onely you deſire to hear) to have ſuch men hold their peace; In the mean time I am ſure, hee hath effected his will upon us, in a great meaſure another way, by ſending theſe his Chaplains amongſt us. Inſomuch, that many men in <hi>England</hi> may bee ſaid to wander, as <hi>Amos</hi> ſpeaks <hi>Chap.</hi> 8. not from <hi>Sea to Sea,</hi> nor from the <hi>north to the weſt;</hi> but from pariſh to pariſh to <hi>ſeek the Word of God, and cannot find it ver.</hi> 11.12.</p>
               <p>As let any knowing, and experimentall <hi>Chriſtian</hi> go to <hi>hundreds of pariſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in England,</hi> and hear but what preachers they have; yea, have choſen for themſelvs (for by their good wills they will admit of no other then
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170108:17"/>theſe or worſe.) Or rather let there bee a ſurvey made, throughout the <hi>three Nations;</hi> and the number taken: firſt of ſuch as preach ſo <hi>unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly,</hi> that the people are never the better for their preaching; ſecondly of <hi>ſcandalous Miniſters,</hi> that pull down either with <hi>one</hi> or <hi>both hands;</hi> that is to ſay with their <hi>lewd lives,</hi> or by their <hi>devilliſh doctrine;</hi> thirdly of <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine preachers,</hi> who inſtead of edifying to <hi>ſalvation,</hi> do edifie to <hi>damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> being very Rhetoricall to <hi>diſcourage the godly,</hi> and <hi>incourage the wicked;</hi> rarely eloquent to <hi>flatter ſin,</hi> and <hi>flout holineſs.</hi> And you will ſay, that <hi>God</hi> is as much beholding to hundreds of the beſt of them for their pains in preaching, and receivs as much good by their labour in the <hi>Church,</hi> as doth a <hi>Farmer</hi> by thoſe <hi>quick cattle</hi> which continually live in his <hi>barn, feed upon his corn,</hi> and though they do him no great hurt, yet hee hath no <hi>ſervice</hi> from them at all. Yea, I doubt not, but themſelvs, I mean theſe non-preachers, theſe witty preachers will one day (If ever <hi>God</hi> bee pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to open their eyes) acknowledge as much; and as much diſdain to preach ſo, as now they do the contrary. For as the <hi>Jews,</hi> when they heard the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> preach, <hi>burnt their curious books, and had no more delight</hi> to ſtudy ſuch toies: ſo as theſe Miniſters come to the knowledge, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of the truth; and to have their eyes opened: they will bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to leave theſe fancies, and ſay with <hi>Saint Paul, I deſire to know, or preach nothing but Chriſt and him crucified.</hi> And indeed, there is but <hi>one right way</hi> of preaching; that is, when <hi>ſound doctrine,</hi> and <hi>home-application</hi> goes together; many <hi>indirect ways: God</hi> chargeth his Miniſters to refuſe all ways but one, <hi>Satan</hi> bids them refuſe that one, and take which way they pleaſe. Now whether <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>Satan</hi> is moſt heard, and obeyed, I leave for the indifferent <hi>Reader</hi> to iudge. In the mean time, theſe <hi>barren Trees,</hi> that <hi>occupy</hi> the <hi>room</hi> where <hi>better trees</hi> might <hi>grow;</hi> are not onely liable to a fearfull curſe, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.7. <hi>Ezek</hi> 3.17, 18, 19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16. <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.17. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.12.19. but have made themſelves guilty of the blood of the <hi>Lords</hi> people; in taking upon them to bee their <hi>Captains,</hi> and <hi>conductors;</hi> and yet have no skill at all, in managing of <hi>martial affairs:</hi> being like that <hi>Souldier,</hi> who was very diligent in ſcowring of his <hi>Musket,</hi> preparing his <hi>match,</hi> practiſing his <hi>poſtures,</hi> &amp;c. but when hee came into the <hi>field,</hi> had forgot his <hi>powder;</hi> or ſome careleſs <hi>Carpenter,</hi> that ſhould <hi>ſquare</hi> all by his <hi>rule,</hi> but ſticks it at his back, and <hi>works by aim.</hi> For this I may boldly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that all ſuch as come to this <hi>spirituall warfare</hi> with <hi>carnal weapons;</hi> and ſtrive to <hi>encounter</hi> that <hi>ſpirituall Goliah,</hi> with <hi>Sauls harneſs,</hi> and not with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids ſling:</hi> with the <hi>blunt ſword</hi> of meer humane eloquence, the words of men, <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> and <hi>Fathers</hi> only; and not with the <hi>ſharp two-edged ſword</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> the <hi>Word of God:</hi> ſhew themſelvs more like the Devills depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, then <hi>Chriſts Vicars.</hi> For inſtead of preaching the Word, they bring a famine of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section</hi> 16.</head>
               <p>And great pity it is, they are not <hi>caſt out of Churches;</hi> and for ever ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenced, as many of them have been for ſome years, (did they not daily creep in again, by means of ſuch, whoſe ſouls they have formerly poiſoned, and bewitched with their <hi>Philoſophy, and vain deceit,</hi> Coloſ. 2.8.) <hi>Becauſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170108:17"/>ſo long as hee ſupplies the Room of a Minister, hee keeps out another</hi> that would <hi>Preach better:</hi> and perhaps <hi>ſave thoſe poor ſouls,</hi> whom <hi>hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An ill man</hi> in the Church is but like ſome <hi>Shrubby Tree</hi> in a <hi>Garden,</hi> whoſe ſhade not onely keeps better plants from growing; but draws away the nouriſhment from the reſt that would bear us fruit. Or as a great <hi>Oak</hi> in a <hi>Grove,</hi> which not onely <hi>pines</hi> all the <hi>under-woods</hi> near it, but ſpoiles the <hi>Graſs</hi> that ſhould feed the <hi>Cattell.</hi> So that it were better for the <hi>Pariſh</hi> to have no Miniſter at all, then ſuch an one. For though it bee miſerable to want food for the ſoul; yet a <hi>blank</hi> does far better in a <hi>room,</hi> then an <hi>ill-filling.</hi> But how much better would a godly, faithfull, and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous preacher placed in his room bee? who by <hi>Gods</hi> bleſſing would feed thoſe ſouls, whom hee ſtarves; and ſave thoſe, whom hee lets periſh.</p>
               <p>A conſcionable Miniſter, reſembles <hi>David,</hi> who would venter on a <hi>Bear,</hi> rather then loſe a <hi>Lamb;</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> who would endure <hi>heat by day,</hi> and <hi>froſt by night,</hi> rather then neglect his <hi>flocks;</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> who would <hi>fight with odds,</hi> rather then the <hi>cattle</hi> ſhould <hi>periſh</hi> with <hi>thirſt.</hi> Onely ſuch a <hi>Balaam</hi> as theſe, wants this mercy. But what's the reaſon? The <hi>hireling careth not for the ſheep,</hi> Joh. 10.13. <hi>they are not his own,</hi> and what minds hee, whether they bee <hi>fat</hi> or <hi>lean.</hi> A mercenary <hi>advocate</hi> looks one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to his <hi>fee,</hi> let his <hi>clients cauſe stand</hi> or <hi>ſall,</hi> it is all one to him, ſo long as he hath his <hi>money.</hi> A <hi>Capon</hi> that hath moulted away all his <hi>feathers,</hi> and is <hi>cold</hi> and <hi>naked,</hi> in the abſence of the <hi>Hen</hi> will run to her <hi>neſt;</hi> not for any love to the <hi>Chickens,</hi> but to <hi>warm</hi> his own ſides.</p>
               <p>But let ſuch look to it; for they have a fearful reckoning to make, and deſtruction is threatned to every <hi>Prophet</hi> that thus conceals the truth, or forbears to reprove ſin ſharply, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.17, 18, 19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16. <hi>For if they had ſtood in my counſel,</hi> ſaies <hi>God; and had cauſed my people to hear my words: then they ſhould have turned them from their evil way, and from the evil of their doings,</hi> Jer. 23.21, 22. Whereas now, whenſoever thou ſhalt hear the <hi>bell toul</hi> for a <hi>wicked man,</hi> thou maiſt cry out, <hi>There is a ſoul going to hell, whoſe blood will be required at my hands,</hi> becauſ I was not faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and did not give him warning, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.18, 19.</p>
               <p>Indeed theſe <hi>men-pleaſers</hi> may ſeem to bee <hi>neuters,</hi> (as doing neither <hi>good</hi> nor <hi>harm</hi>) or at leaſt more excuſable, and leſſe principal in blood-guiltineſſe, then thoſe unpreaching Miniſters I am yet to ſpeak of; who <hi>flatter ſin,</hi> and <hi>flout holineſſe; diſcourage the godly,</hi> and <hi>incourage the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,</hi> by <hi>falſe-wresting,</hi> or <hi>miſ-applying the Word;</hi> (in that <hi>ſtarving</hi> the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſeems not altogether ſo bad as <hi>poiſoning</hi> them) and to be more excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable, but the truth is, they are no leſſe guilty of the peoples blood; for they are <hi>traitors to God and his kingdome,</hi> and <hi>guilty</hi> of the peoples <hi>blood,</hi> whom <hi>Christ the chief Shepherd</hi> hath committed to their charge. For if a man will take upon him the office of a <hi>Pastor,</hi> and yet not <hi>feed</hi> his people that depend upon him: to bee an <hi>Embaſſadour,</hi> and yet not declare <hi>God's meſſage</hi> to the people: to be their <hi>Phyſician,</hi> and yet not ſee to the peoples
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170108:18"/>
                  <hi>health;</hi> doth he not make himſelf guilty of their miſcarriage, and betray the truſt which was committed unto him? it cannot be denied. The <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate</hi> that is <hi>retained</hi> to <hi>plead,</hi> betraies the cauſe by his voluntary <hi>ſilence:</hi> the <hi>Watchman</hi> that doth not <hi>ring the alarum-bell</hi> at the approach of danger, <hi>betraies</hi> the <hi>city</hi> to the <hi>enemy:</hi> he that will take upon him to be a <hi>leader,</hi> when he cannot inſtruct <hi>God's people</hi> in the <hi>ſpiritual warfare,</hi> betraies the truſt which was committed unto him, and gives great advantage to <hi>Satan</hi> and his miniſters, who are far more induſtrious in their generation, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.25. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.11.</p>
               <p>Neither is there any difference between the <hi>ſhepheards deſtroying the ſheep</hi> with his own hands, or <hi>leaving them</hi> to the mercy of the <hi>Wolf;</hi> or of a <hi>Captains giving up a Caſtle,</hi> or <hi>not defending it</hi> againſt the <hi>enemy,</hi> when it is <hi>beſieged.</hi> What difference between <hi>not-ſaving,</hi> and <hi>deſtroying?</hi> Not to water a plant when it is dry, is to kill it: And the fire is as well put out by the <hi>ſubtraction</hi> of fewel, as by <hi>powring water</hi> upon it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section</hi> 17.</head>
               <p>Nor are theſe Non-preachers more guilty of the people blood, then the people are of their own; for all that forſake their faithful Paſtors, whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath placed over them, to follow theſe <hi>mountebanks,</hi> are in the ſight of <hi>God wilful murtherers of their own ſouls.</hi> For as when <hi>God</hi> had given the <hi>children of Iſrael Sampſon;</hi> to deliver them out of the hands of the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtims,</hi> that ſo much oppreſſed them, they ſpared not to betray him them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to deliver him bound into their oppreſſers hands, <hi>Judg.</hi> 15. when yet he was the onely deliverer that <hi>God</hi> had appointed them: or as <hi>Jephtha</hi> was rejected of his brethren, and yet the Lord appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and intended no other to ſave and deliver them but him: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as <hi>Chriſt,</hi> albeit he came to his own, yet they received him not, but diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully refuſed him; and yet the <hi>Lord</hi> decreed him to bee the onely Saviour of his people; and that by no other means or <hi>name under heaven we ſhould look for ſalvation, but by the Name of JESUS,</hi> Acts 4.12. So they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and perſecute their faithful Paſtor whom <hi>God</hi> hath ſet over them, and ſent to be their <hi>deliverer</hi> from the <hi>thraldom</hi> of <hi>ſin and Satan:</hi> and proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly reſolved to ſave them by him, and none elſe. Yea, they will <hi>hear, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, applaud</hi> and <hi>reward</hi> theſe men-pleaſers, theſe ſoul-murtherers; while in the mean time <hi>Chriſts</hi> faithful meſſengers ſhall meet with nothing from them but <hi>contempt, hatred, baſe language,</hi> and <hi>blows.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But fools as they are, the caſe will be ſtrangely altered: for come they once to a ſence and ſight of their ſad condition, as when they <hi>lie gaſping at their laſt hour,</hi> they will wiſh, O that I had now but the opportunity to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with ſuch a Miniſter! As <hi>Saul</hi> ſleighted <hi>Samuel</hi> while hee <hi>lived,</hi> but would ſain have heard, and adviſed with him when he was <hi>dead. He</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) that rebuketh a man, ſhall finde more favour at the length, then he which flattereth with his tongue,</hi> Prov. 28.23. a point well worth theſe mens minding.</p>
               <p>And the ſame touching <hi>the cauſe</hi> of their diſlike, as obſerve I pray you; <hi>Manna</hi> we know had no fault, but that it was too <hi>good,</hi> and too <hi>frequent;</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:170108:18"/>onely the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> liked it not; and indeed the <hi>pulſe of Egypt</hi> had been fitter for their <hi>courſe ſtomachs:</hi> and ſo is <hi>poetry, Roman hiſtory,</hi> &amp;c. ſweeter unto theſe mens <hi>ears, which are ſo groſſe of hearing:</hi> But where lies the fault? Look into thy ſelf, that <hi>heavenly bread</hi> was <hi>unſpeakably delicious,</hi> it <hi>taſted like wafers of honey;</hi> and yet even this <hi>Angels food</hi> is <hi>contemned. He that is full despiſeth the honey comb:</hi> and no leſſe ſweet is the <hi>Gospel,</hi> not onely the <hi>Fathers of the Old Teſtament,</hi> but the <hi>Angels deſired to look into the glorious myſteries of it;</hi> and yet thou art <hi>cloied,</hi> this <hi>ſupernatural food</hi> is <hi>too light, the bread-corn of humane reaſon</hi> and profound diſcourſe will bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter content thee.</p>
               <p>But little do'ſt thou think what a damnable ſin this is, and what it will coſt thee another day, if thou continueſt in the ſame mind. For <hi>this is the condemnation,</hi> [none like this] <hi>that light is come into the world, and men loved darkneſſe rather then light, becauſe their deeds were evil,</hi> Joh. 3.19. And ſo on the contrary, <hi>This is life eternal; to know thee the onely true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent,</hi> Joh. 17.3.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section</hi> 18.</head>
               <p>But the miſery is! there is no perſwading theſe men that they are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of <hi>God,</hi> or of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> What they ignorant perſons? when they are the onely <hi>lovers of wit</hi> and knowledg, which makes them frequent theſe <hi>witty preachers;</hi> nor can they endure your <hi>dull drones.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which I anſwer, This <hi>wit</hi> in Scripture language, and in <hi>Gods</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, is <hi>fooliſhneſſe,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. and <hi>enmity againſt the wiſdom of God.</hi> Rom. 8.7. So that as <hi>wiſe Solomon</hi> ſpeaks, there is <hi>more hope of a fools becoming wiſe, then of theſe mens, that are wiſe in their own conceit,</hi> Prov. 26.12. And as <hi>love</hi> and <hi>luſt</hi> are not <hi>all one;</hi> ſo a <hi>witty,</hi> and a <hi>wiſe-man</hi> is not <hi>all one. The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wiſdome, and to depart from evil is underſtanding,</hi> Job 28.28. And <hi>hereby,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>John, is it known that we know God, if wee keep his commandements,</hi> 1 Joh. 2.3. <hi>But he that ſaith I know him, and yet keepeth not his commandements, is a lier and there is no truth in him,</hi> ver. 4. He onely is wiſe, that is <hi>wiſe for his own ſoul.</hi> If they were wiſe ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi> they would fore-ſee the torments of hell, and prevent them. Alas! one ſpark of <hi>ſpiritual experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental and ſaving knowledg,</hi> guided by the fear of <hi>God,</hi> is more worth then all ſecular wiſedom and learning, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.16, 17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15, 16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.10. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.45. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.15.</p>
               <p>But this <hi>wiſdome deſcendeth from above, and keepeth a man from every evil way,</hi> Prov. 2.12. and <hi>God</hi> onely is the giver of it, and he gives it to none but his children the godly, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.14. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.45. <hi>Mark</hi> 4.34. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.17. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1, 7. It is not ſo much <hi>ſcientia capitis,</hi> as <hi>conſcientia cordis</hi> that knows <hi>Christ,</hi> and <hi>our ſelves:</hi> Whence <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Give thine heart to wiſdom,</hi> Prov. 2.10. and, <hi>Let wiſdome enter into thine heart,</hi> Prov. 4.4. <hi>The natural man perceiveth not the things of the Spirit of God; neither can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.14. and indeed if they are ſpiritually diſcerned, how ſhould they diſcern them that have not the <hi>ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:170108:19"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> You ſeem to condemn all that frequent theſe witty Preachers; do you think none of their hearers <hi>good,</hi> nor <hi>wiſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this I will make a <hi>three-fold anſwer;</hi> the firſt ſhall be in the words of <hi>our Saviour Chriſt,</hi> and of Saint <hi>John: They are of the world</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>John</hi>) <hi>therefore ſpeak they of the world, and the world hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them. Wee are of God; he that knoweth God, heareth us; he that is not of God, heareth us not. Hereby know wee the Spirit of truth, and the ſpirit of error,</hi> 1 Joh. 4.5, 6. And again, <hi>Hee that is of God, heareth Gods words: Yee therefore hear them not, becauſe yee are not of God,</hi> Joh. 8.47. <hi>Every one that is of the truth</hi> (ſaies our Saviour) <hi>heareth my voice,</hi> Job. 18.37. <hi>Chriſts ſheep know not the voice of a ſtranger; neither will they hear or follow ſtrangers, or hirelings; becauſe they care not for the ſheep.</hi> But as <hi>they know Chriſts voice,</hi> ſo <hi>him onely will they follow, and fly from a ſtranger,</hi> as you have it <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.3, 4, 5, 13, 14, 27. Now if we would know, whether a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter comes in Chriſts name,</hi> or in <hi>his own;</hi> whether hee <hi>be of God,</hi> or <hi>of the world:</hi> wee need no better note, then to obſerve what his hearers are. For uſually if the Church of ſuch a preacher ſhould be ſearched, as <hi>Jehu</hi> and <hi>Jehonadab</hi> did the houſe of <hi>Ball,</hi> there is ſcarce a ſervant of the Lord amongſt them. Their <hi>judgments</hi> being ſo <hi>diametrially oppoſite,</hi> that <hi>what preaching the one loves, the other loaths.</hi> Neither would their hearers ſo applaud or approve of them, if they were of <hi>Gods ſending. I am come in my Fathers name, ſaith our Saviour, and yee receive me not: if another ſhall come in his own name, him you will receive,</hi> Joh. 5.43.</p>
               <p>Men of the <hi>world</hi> will not hear ſuch preachers as are of <hi>God:</hi> becauſe then they muſt have their conſciences terrefied about their ſins, (or elſe part with them) and be told of the fearful condition they are in: yea the greateſt of ſinners affect more the <hi>flattery of falſe Prophets,</hi> then the <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of Chriſts faithful meſſengers,</hi> Iſa. 30.10. Mica. 2.11. But it's eaſie to diſcern where the fault lies, and who is to be blamed. For 'tis onely the <hi>weak-ſighted</hi> that <hi>cannot abide the light:</hi> and none can diſlike the word of truth, but ſuch as have an <hi>over-flowing of their gall,</hi> or an <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weening of their wit:</hi> ſuch as are both <hi>ſhameleſſe</hi> and <hi>graceleſſe.</hi> As do you ſee an <hi>Apple fall</hi> untimely <hi>from the tree,</hi> view it well, and you will finde it <hi>worm-eaten,</hi> elſe it had <hi>held.</hi> But ſuch as have a <hi>blemiſh in their eie, think the element to be over cloudy.</hi> Our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelf could neither ſpeak, or do ought, but ſuch would be offended at it. In which caſe who is to be blamed? Is the <hi>Phyſitian</hi> to be blamed for the <hi>pain</hi> of his <hi>Patient,</hi> or the <hi>diſeaſe?</hi> the <hi>Chirurgion,</hi> or the <hi>wound</hi> which he indeavours by all means to <hi>cure?</hi> Yea, tell mee what is the cauſe? why the worſt men, and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in a pariſh, evermore regard a good Miniſter leaſt; complain of his bitterneſſe, and ſeek by all means to remove him? Is it not becauſe they are <hi>feet,</hi> and <hi>legs,</hi> and <hi>thighs,</hi> and <hi>arms out of joint,</hi> and ſo cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the <hi>touch of the Chirurgions hand,</hi> and the <hi>acrimony of his medicines.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section</hi> 19.</head>
               <p>Secondly, my next Anſwer to the former queſtion is, <hi>Their practice proves it.</hi> For this you may take for a general rule, that if theſe brave Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170108:19"/>theſe unhallowed Divines, have ap plauſ, and be cried up for rare Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, it is from men as <hi>carnal</hi> and <hi>graceleſſe</hi> as themſelvs. As look but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their lives, and ſee if they be not like people that have a diſeaſe <hi>called the Wolf;</hi> which is alwaies <hi>eating,</hi> yet keeps the body <hi>lean.</hi> They have long heard, and ſtill deſire to hear their ſermons: yet they grow not by their hearing; for like thoſe <hi>ſeaven ill-favoured and lean-fleſhed Kine,</hi> Gen. 41.20, 21. <hi>it cannot be known that they have heard them:</hi> for they are not onely <hi>as lean and ill-favored Chriſtians ſtill as</hi> they were <hi>before</hi> they heard them, but much <hi>worſe.</hi> For as touching that is good, that they let paſſe; it faring with their <hi>memories</hi> as with an <hi>hour-glaſs,</hi> or <hi>Conduit;</hi> that which in <hi>one hour runneth in,</hi> the ſame in <hi>another hour runneth out again:</hi> Onely the evil wil they keep to increaſe their prejudice, and to fore-ſtall them againſt goodneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Whereby may we know and judg of a wicked man? for we muſt not pronounce any man a <hi>leper,</hi> till wee ſee the <hi>ſcab.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> by his <hi>works,</hi> and by his <hi>words;</hi> every <hi>tree is known by the fruits:</hi> It is <hi>Chriſts</hi> everlaſting rule, however the <hi>tree lives</hi> by the <hi>ſap,</hi> and not by the <hi>fruit;</hi> yet it is known to live by the <hi>fruit,</hi> and not by the <hi>ſap,</hi> for this is hid. When the <hi>Conduit is walled in,</hi> how ſhall wee judge of the ſpring? but by the water that runs out of the pipes. The <hi>outward actions,</hi> declare the <hi>inward intentions.</hi> Men do ſomtimes bewray that by their deeds, which to confeſs they are hardly drawn.</p>
               <p>As in <hi>a clock</hi> when the <hi>hammer</hi> ſtrikes well, and the <hi>hand</hi> of the diall points well; it is a ſigne that the wheels are right ſet. Yea by the <hi>pointing of the hand alone,</hi> wee may know how the clock goes within: And ſo by the <hi>ſtriking of the hammer,</hi> which is the ſecond rule.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Speech</hi> is the <hi>index</hi> of the <hi>minde,</hi> for <hi>out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh, Matth.</hi> 12.34. Whence obſerve, that <hi>a good man out of the good treaſury of his heart, bringeth forth good things: and an evill man out of the evil treaſury of his heart, bringeth forth evill things, Matth.</hi> 12.35. As the <hi>bell</hi> is known by his <hi>ſound;</hi> ſo a man is by nothing better known, then by his <hi>communication,</hi> ſays <hi>Seneca: evill ſpeaking</hi> diſcovers an <hi>evill heart:</hi> as the <hi>ſtriking</hi> of the <hi>clapper</hi> does a broken <hi>bell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea, men may bee known by their <hi>want of fruit:</hi> wee may ſuſpect want of <hi>ſap</hi> in the <hi>root</hi> of a <hi>tree;</hi> if wee find <hi>barrenneſs in the branches:</hi> if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it have <hi>bad fruit, or no fruit,</hi> it is but a dead <hi>faith.</hi> And the true me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of grace is, <hi>Ceaſe to do evill, learn to do well, Iſa.</hi> 1.16, 17. For as <hi>grace enters into the heart, ſo ſin goes out:</hi> like air out of a <hi>veſſell,</hi> when <hi>wine</hi> is poured in; or as it fares with <hi>women,</hi> that having once <hi>conceived,</hi> cannot admit of <hi>another conception,</hi> untill they be delivered of the firſt, ſee <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24.</p>
               <p>I grant there bee multitudes of them that appear not wicked no every mans capacity; for ſome of them and not a few, are civill and <hi>fair</hi> in their <hi>carriages, ſmooth</hi> in their <hi>communication;</hi> and for the moſt part, unreprov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: yet this you ſhall bee ſure to find, that they are <hi>bitter malignants
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170108:20"/>to the power of religion,</hi> and <hi>ſcoffers at holineſs:</hi> and there needs no more to prove them wicked.</p>
               <p>I grant they may bee morally honeſt, temperate, chaſt, charitable, go du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Church, pray in their families, abſtain in ſome meaſure from <hi>ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, lying,</hi> and the like: But does this flow from a pious and good heart, ſanctified by the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Act.</hi> 15.9. Is it done in <hi>faith,</hi> and out of <hi>right ends:</hi> as out of <hi>love,</hi> and <hi>obedience;</hi> becauſe <hi>God</hi> commands the ſame, that hee may bee glorified, and others edified thereby; for otherwiſe all their performances are no better in <hi>Gods</hi> account, then <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of an Idol, or cutting off a dogs neck,</hi> as the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſhews <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58. <hi>Chap.</hi> and 66.3. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.22.13.</p>
               <p>Again, do you <hi>pay God his dues</hi> alſo? do you <hi>repent</hi> and <hi>beleev the Goſpel pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and menaces,</hi> aſwel as <hi>promiſes?</hi> do you <hi>declare your faith by your works?</hi> do you pray <hi>by the power of the Spirit, and with the underſtanding alſo?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15. do you <hi>receive the word with good and honeſt hearts?</hi> and alſo <hi>bring forth the fruits of it,</hi> in your life and converſation? do you <hi>ſanctifie his ſabbaths,</hi> and ſee that all under you do the ſame: <hi>love his children, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote his glory, and strive to gain others</hi> to imbrace the <hi>Gospell? inſtruct your children and ſervants?</hi> and <hi>teach them to fear the Lord?</hi> do you <hi>fear an oath, hate a lye, &amp;c. Love zeal,</hi> and devotion <hi>in others?</hi> make conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of <hi>evill thoughts? vain and unprofitable words?</hi> grieve for your <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitableneſs</hi> under the means of grace? for the <hi>evill which cleavs to your very beſt actions? for ſins of omiſſion &amp;c.</hi> No, you may bee good <hi>morall honeſt hypocrites;</hi> but none of theſe graces grow in the <hi>gardens of your hearts;</hi> you have a form of <hi>godlineſs,</hi> but you deny <hi>the power of it, and are reprobate to every good work,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Titus</hi> 1.16. Yea, have you not <hi>ſtrange conceits, and baſe thoughts of the best men?</hi> do you not deeply cenſure <hi>and condemn the generation of the just?</hi> and think the worſe of a man for having a tender conſcience? do you not <hi>envy, hate, ſcoffe at, nick-name, rail on, and ſlander the people of God;</hi> and <hi>miſconstrue their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and intentions? watch for their haulting,</hi> &amp;c. Do you not with <hi>Feſtus, account zeal madneſs; and religion fooliſhneſs, with Micholl?</hi> Yea, you hate zeal and devotion ſo invetterately; that you can in no wiſe bear with it in others. And does not all this prove thee wicked? though righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous enough in thine own eyes. But</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section</hi> 20.</head>
               <p>Thirdly, and laſtly; there needs no more to prove them ignorant, then their rejecting to hear the Word plainly preached; chuſing rather to hear a lecture of <hi>Philoſophie</hi> read: As it's ſtrange to conſider, how groſly men err in judging of things, that take not the Word for their rule; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſome inſtances. Such ſhall think <hi>they do God ſervice in murthering his Children and Prophets, John</hi> 16.2. And ſo did the <hi>Powder Traitors,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to <hi>blow up the whole State.</hi> They think to bee ſaved by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> though they do nothing but blaſpheme him, and take up arms againſt him. They will ſay, they <hi>love God and Chriſt,</hi> and yet hate all that any way re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170108:20"/>him. They will boaſt of a ſtrong faith, and yet fall ſhort of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills in beleeving, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.19. The <hi>Jews accuſed Chriſt</hi> for keeping com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with ſinners, when they ſhould have blamed themſelvs for not keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing company with <hi>Christ. God hath given mee my reward,</hi> ſays <hi>Leah; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I gave my maid unto my husband:</hi> ſhee <hi>rejoiced,</hi> when ſhee ſhould have <hi>repented, Gen.</hi> 30.18. And the like of <hi>Saul, Bleſſed are yee of the Lord</hi> ſays hee, when the <hi>Ziphims</hi> told him where <hi>David</hi> had hid himſelf: his intent being to murther him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.21. And like to this, is that of <hi>Micha,</hi> who thought the <hi>Lord</hi> could not chooſe but bee good unto him; ſeeing hee had got a <hi>Levite</hi> into his houſe, <hi>Judg.</hi> 17.13. In like manner, what is the cauſe of theſe mens preferring theſe preachers? but their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of <hi>Gods Word:</hi> they do not in the leaſt perceive the things of the Spirit; they are ſpiritually blind, and ſo not able to judge of <hi>preaching,</hi> or <hi>Preachers.</hi> Being like <hi>ſhell-fiſh</hi> that cannot ſmell; or the <hi>Camelion</hi> which hath no taſt: and withall ſo improvident touching their ſouls, that they will rather <hi>take droſs for gold,</hi> then try it in the <hi>furnace;</hi> whence it is they reſemble <hi>Alchidas,</hi> who was enamored on the <hi>Picture of Cupid;</hi> or <hi>Zerxes,</hi> who fell ſo far in love with a <hi>Plane-tree</hi> which happened in his way, that hee tarried by it a whole day; cauſing the <hi>boughs to bee adorned with chains of gold, bracelets, and spangles, yielding thereto great reverence.</hi> But did they tread in the ſteps of all wiſe and good Chriſtians, who have <hi>the mind of Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16. or acquainted with Gods Word, and judg of things and perſons as they are, and not as they ſeem, (whoſe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony onely is of credit); they would bee ſo far from <hi>applauding</hi> the men, that they would not vouchſafe to hear their ſermons.</p>
               <p>Now if any ſhall yet make queſtion of their ignorance, do but ask them a reaſon of the hope that is in them; (as every one that profeſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> ſhould be able and ready to yeeld, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15.) they can no more tell you, then the wind can tell which laſt blew off my hat. All <hi>expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimentall divinity, is greek</hi> to them, bee they never ſo great lovers of wit. Indeed to ſpeak <hi>againſt the truth,</hi> their tongues will <hi>run like the wheels of a clock,</hi> when the <hi>ſpring is broken:</hi> but they are neither able, nor willing to ſpeak a word for it.</p>
               <p>Now if theſe things be ſo, then they whom they hear and honor, have ſmall cauſe to rejoice therein: Nor have the other whom they ſhun and hate, any cauſe to be diſcouraged thereby, becauſe to carnal and fleſhly men, that <hi>preaching</hi> which ſaves ſouls, is <hi>fooliſhneſs; devotion, idleneſs;</hi> the <hi>Prophets, mad-men; Paul, a babbler.</hi> And untill they be cured <hi>of their prejudice, (which God onely by his prerogative can do) nothing that can be ſaid will ſerve. Wiſdom,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>is juſtified of her children;</hi> that is the faithful, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.19. intimating, that ſuch wiſdom as is juſtified by wicked men, is not wiſdom indeed. Take we then our Saviours counſel, and ſeek to juſtifie our judgments to the <hi>children of wiſdom,</hi> of whom wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is <hi>juſtified;</hi> and not to <hi>fools,</hi> by whom ſhe is daily crucified. And tread in his ſteps who rejected <hi>the commendations and approbation of ſuch, Luk.</hi> 4.35, 41. and Saint <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 16.17, 18.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:170108:21"/>
               <p> True, as the <hi>Church of Laodicea</hi> could flatter her ſelf with an opinion, that ſhe was <hi>rich, and had need of nothing:</hi> when yet ſhe was <hi>wretched, and miſerable, and poor, and blind, and naked,</hi> Rev. 3.17. Or as the <hi>young man in the Goſpel,</hi> could brag that <hi>he had kept all the commandements from his youth,</hi> Mat. 19.20. And that cackling <hi>Phariſee, Luk.</hi> 18.11, 12. <hi>could tell Chriſt, that hee was not like other men:</hi> ſo there is no perſwading theſe men, but they are wiſe and good enough; and no wonder, for they <hi>ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and ſuppoſe themſelvs good Chriſtians:</hi> their <hi>faith</hi> is but a <hi>dream,</hi> their <hi>hope</hi> but a <hi>dream,</hi> their <hi>charity</hi> but a <hi>dream,</hi> their <hi>obedience</hi> but a <hi>dream,</hi> their whole <hi>religion</hi> but a <hi>dream,</hi> and ſo their <hi>aſſurance of ſalvation</hi> is but a <hi>dream.</hi> They have <hi>Regeneration</hi> in <hi>conceit, repentance</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſs in conceit;</hi> they <hi>ſerve God</hi> well in <hi>conceit,</hi> do the <hi>works of piety</hi> and <hi>charity</hi> in <hi>cenceit;</hi> and they ſhall go to <hi>heaven onely in conceit,</hi> or in a <hi>dream,</hi> and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>awake,</hi> until they <hi>feel</hi> themſelvs really in the <hi>burning lake.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, do but take away from mens minds <hi>vain opinions, flattering hopes, falſe valuations, imaginations,</hi> and the like, you will leave the mindes of moſt men and women but <hi>poor ſhrunken things,</hi> full of <hi>melancholy, indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,</hi> and <hi>unpleaſing to themſelvs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which could never be, if <hi>Satan the Prince of darkneſſe, and of this world,</hi> did not ſo <hi>blind their minds, that the light of the glorious Goſpel ſhines not unto them,</hi> as it is, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. And would they but lend the <hi>Gospel</hi> an ear, where it is <hi>powerfully preached;</hi> they would at leaſt be ſo wiſe, as to get <hi>better aſſurance,</hi> then onely to <hi>think themſelvs</hi> good enough; ſince pure and naked <hi>ſuppoſals</hi> never brought any one to <hi>eternal life.</hi> Neither is there any other means to be uſed, whereby it is to be had. Onely the skill is, to perſwade the ſimple (as to be wiſe and ſolid is the portion but of a few) to beware of hearing theſe fruitleſſe Preachers; or indeed any others that preach not point-blank againſt <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>ignorance;</hi> that diſcover not <hi>Satans wiles,</hi> and the <hi>hearts deceitfulneſs;</hi> that preach not <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>free grace;</hi> that preſſe not to <hi>Repentance, Regeneration,</hi> and the like; that make not the <hi>glory of God,</hi> and the <hi>good of ſouls,</hi> the main end of their preaching. As why do, or why ſhould men go to <hi>hear,</hi> if not for <hi>profit</hi> and <hi>comfort</hi> to their ſouls? (<hi>Good ſtomachs</hi> make better account of <hi>wholſome fare,</hi> then of <hi>dainty cates.</hi>) Why, but to <hi>hear</hi> the good Word of GOD? that they may <hi>grow</hi> thereby, and to be <hi>nouriſhed.</hi> Now <hi>nouriſhment</hi> is the making of <hi>food received,</hi> like to the <hi>bodie nouriſhed:</hi> Therefore a wiſe Chriſtian affects to hear powerful preaching, ſearching Sermons, rather then run after <hi>Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricians;</hi> becauſe the rarities of humane eloquence works no <hi>ſuch effect,</hi> nor tends to any <hi>ſuch end.</hi> For <hi>Philoſophie</hi> and ſuch like may <hi>civilize,</hi> but not <hi>ſanctifie; hide</hi> ſome ſins, but not <hi>heal</hi> them; <hi>cover,</hi> not <hi>cure</hi> them; <hi>harb,</hi> and <hi>curb</hi> them; not <hi>abate,</hi> and <hi>aboliſh</hi> them. Yea, we may ſay of their <hi>problemes,</hi> as the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> did of the <hi>Athenian-ſhops,</hi> How many things are here that we <hi>have no need of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore I ſhall conclude with an Exhortation, or Advertiſement to theſe <hi>men,</hi> to uſe this <hi>means,</hi> and to affect that <hi>food</hi> which is <hi>wholſom,</hi> and would nouriſh. O! that <hi>I might prevail</hi> with them, to hear either <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:170108:21"/>or <hi>reaſon,</hi> though my betters cannot; for then would they finde it the happieſt counſel that ever they met with. Nor am I altogether out of hope; for though <hi>all the water in the ſea</hi> will not <hi>waſh</hi> a <hi>Blackmore</hi> white; yet others with <hi>Naaman,</hi> may <hi>waſh</hi> and be <hi>clean.</hi> Nor can it be denied, but an <hi>Emperick</hi> now and then hath had the hap to cure a <hi>patient,</hi> which a <hi>learned Artiſt</hi> could not do.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>Section 21. <hi>An</hi> Advertiſement <hi>to all</hi> uncircumciſed hearts and ears, exhorting them to hear the Word of GOD <hi>purely and powerfully preached; and not to liſten after ſuch, as ſeek onely to pleaſe the ear with</hi> rarities of humane eloquence, and the inticing words of man's wiſdom.</head>
               <p>IF there be <hi>any</hi> (if but <hi>one,</hi> even <hi>thy ſelf,</hi>) that ſhall by what I have ſaid, be induced to <hi>judg</hi> of things <hi>according to</hi> clear <hi>truth,</hi> not <hi>blinded opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> and be willing to <hi>depart</hi> from this diſcourſe <hi>better then they came to it,</hi> let him in the firſt place know, that the onely ordinary means of grace and converſion, is by <hi>hearing the word of God</hi> impartially and powerfully prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and by <hi>entertaining it with a good and honeſt heart:</hi> for <hi>this Word,</hi> and <hi>this onely is able to make a man wiſe to ſalvation.</hi> As thus we may ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue; <hi>Without knowledge the heart cannot be good,</hi> Prov. 19.2. A man may <hi>know</hi> the <hi>will</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and yet not <hi>do</hi> it: but he can never <hi>do</hi> it, except firſt he <hi>know</hi> it. Whence, as in the <hi>Creation</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> the <hi>firſt thing that God made, was light,</hi> Gen. 1.3. So when he makes us <hi>new creatures,</hi> he <hi>firſt creates light in the underſtanding,</hi> whereby the poor ſoul may ſee his ſpiritual miſery and wretchedneſſe, which before (by reaſon of <hi>that vail,</hi> or curtain which is <hi>drawn over every natural mans heart,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.14, 15, 16.) he is ſo far from diſcerning, that with <hi>Laodicea,</hi> he thinks <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf rich, and to want nothing;</hi> when yet <hi>he is wretched, and miſerable, and poor, and blind, and naked</hi> of all ſpiritual indowments, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.17. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. <hi>ver.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>Therefore let your principall care and ambition bee; to know thoſe things, the knowledge whereof is eternall life, <hi>John</hi> 17.3. And the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect whereof is of all moſt the damnable, <hi>John</hi> 3.19. Therefore it is ſaid of <hi>Chriſt (whoſe firſt coming was to ſave the world)</hi> that hee will come the <hi>ſecond time, in flaming fire, to render vengeance unto all thoſe that know not God,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.6, 7, 8, 9. A terrible text to all that are ignorant in the midſt of ſo much means as wee injoy. Which being ſo, bee diligent above all, to hear <hi>Chriſts</hi> faithfull meſſengers; And not theſe, who if they preach not wickedly in flattering, or furthering of ſin: yet they preach unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably: as if they were reſolved to connive at ſin, as feeding their flocks rather with words, then matter: as caring onely to pleaſe, not to inform; forming their voice to the liking of their hearers, not their hearers judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the voice of <hi>Chriſt in the Gospell;</hi> and ſtriving more to make them
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170108:22"/>in love with the teacher, then with the leſſon. Becauſe they ſtand more upon their own credit, then their peoples benefit.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Or if they labour to fill the head with knowledge, they leave the heart empty of grace; ſpending their time either in <hi>curious Questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and vain ſpeculations; which kinde of preaching tends rather to mirth, then godly edification; as it is obſervable, that that age of the Church, which was moſt fertile in <hi>Nice Queſtions,</hi> was moſt barren in <hi>Religion.</hi> The reaſon is, it makes people think <hi>Religion</hi> to bee onely a matter of <hi>wit;</hi> as <hi>tying of knots, and untying them.</hi> Wherein the brains of men given this way, are uſually hotter then their hearts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Or if their preaching be more ſolid, they rove altogether in <hi>genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities:</hi> which are no more aiding to practiſe, then an <hi>Ortelius Univerſall Map</hi> is to direct the way between <hi>London</hi> and <hi>York.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Or if they deſcend to particulars, they paſs over the <hi>grounds of Religion,</hi> the moſt uſefull part of all <hi>Divinity.</hi> For this laies the <hi>Foundation,</hi> the other raiſeth the <hi>Walls and Roof.</hi> This informes the <hi>Judgment,</hi> that ſtirs up the <hi>Affections.</hi> And what good uſe is there of thoſe <hi>Affections</hi> which run before the <hi>Judgment?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Or laſtly, If they give you the <hi>grounds of Religion,</hi> and preach whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome truths, yet they bring forth their <hi>Doctrines</hi> as ſome women do their <hi>children, ſtill-born,</hi> for want of application: without which the former ſeems to be no better then a <hi>fair Image,</hi> or <hi>Statue,</hi> which is beautifull to <hi>Contemplate,</hi> but is without <hi>life and motion:</hi> It being the ſoul of preaching, when the <hi>Word</hi> is brought home to mens conſciences, and applied cloſe. For whereas thoſe other Divine diſcourſes, inrich the brain and tongue; This ſettles the heart, changes the will, and works upon the affections.</p>
               <p>The onely way to become <hi>ſuch indeed,</hi> as men <hi>dream themſelvs</hi> to bee, is to truſt <hi>Satan</hi> and their <hi>deceitfull hearts leſs,</hi> and <hi>Gods Word</hi> and <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters more.</hi> This is to <hi>become fools, that they may bee wiſe,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> adviſeth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. Wherefore <hi>receive with meekneſs the ingrafted word which is able to ſave your ſoul, as</hi> Saint James adviſeth, <hi>James</hi> 1. <hi>verſe</hi> 21.</p>
               <p>And that you may not want incouragement, mind but what our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt</hi> ſays, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13. <hi>Verily, verily,</hi> (hee confirms it with a double aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeveration) <hi>I ſay unto you; If I ſend any, hee that receiveth him receiveth mee; and hee that receiveth mee, receiveth him that ſent mee, ver.</hi> 20. Loe, in entertaining the Word with an honeſt and good heart, wee enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain both <hi>God and Chriſt with it.</hi> Another famous place to encourage us in this caſe, is that, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.27.28. too long to repeat, I pray turn to it.</p>
               <p>Again take notice, that as <hi>hunger</hi> is a <hi>ſigne of good health;</hi> ſo to <hi>hunger and thirſt after Gods Word,</hi> is a notable <hi>ſigne of our spirituall health</hi> and ſafety, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.6. Yea, the <hi>ſence</hi> of our <hi>wretchedneſs,</hi> and the <hi>valuation</hi> of our ſpirituall helps, is the beſt <hi>triall</hi> of our <hi>Regeneration.</hi> In the next place,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170108:22"/>delay not the opportunity of hearing: but as the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> ſaith, <hi>Even to day hear his voice, and harden not your hearts, as in the provocation,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.7.8. The <hi>time preſent,</hi> is <hi>the onely time</hi> to ſeek the Lord. To make ſhort, heat the Word indifferently, and impartially: have no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice againſt him thou haſt heretofore moſt hated, and ſlighted; but hear him the rather for his bitterneſſe. Perhaps <hi>God</hi> will convert and ſave thee by no other means, or Miniſter, then ſuch as he hath placed thee under. Deſpiſe not the meaneſt of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Meſſengers, that delivers the Word purely, aims at his glory, and the good of ſouls. And the better to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce you to eſteem ſuch, conſider with me a few particulars.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Section</hi> 22.</head>
               <p>Such Miniſters, as are of <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſending; are not onely appointed of <hi>God</hi> as <hi>watchmen,</hi> to give us warning of enſuing danger, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.17. and <hi>Paſtors,</hi> to feed our ſouls with the ſpiritual <hi>Manna of God's Word,</hi> Eph. 4.11.12. and <hi>Captains,</hi> to fight <hi>God's</hi> battels for us againſt our ſpiritual e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies; and our <hi>Leaders,</hi> to inſtruct us in the ſpiritual warfare, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.12, 13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.3, 4, 5. and <hi>God's Embaſſadors</hi> to declare his will, and meſſage unto us, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.20. and lye <hi>Leigers,</hi> for the <hi>great King of heaven and earth,</hi> (So that whatſoever is <hi>done to them, God takes</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts <hi>as done to him,</hi> Pſal. 44.22.) But they are <hi>co-workers together with God,</hi> in converting and ſaving our ſouls, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Hee ſhall ſpeak words unto thee,</hi> (ſaies the <hi>Angel</hi> to <hi>Cornelius</hi>) <hi>whereby both thou and all thine houſe ſhall be ſaved,</hi> Act. 11.14. Wee are all <hi>born dead</hi> in ſins and treſpaſſes: But what ſaies the Apoſtle <hi>Peter? Unto this purpoſe was the Goſpel preached alſo unto the dead: that they might be condemned accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to men in the fleſh, but might live according to God in the ſpirit,</hi> 1 Pet. 4. ver. 6.</p>
               <p>For <hi>concluſion</hi> of all, hear the Word <hi>in ſeaſon,</hi> and <hi>out of ſeaſon;</hi> and ſo <hi>minde</hi> the ſame; that if any <hi>virtue</hi> be <hi>commended, practiſe</hi> it; if any <hi>vice condemned, avoid it;</hi> if any <hi>conſolation</hi> bee inſinuated, <hi>approoriate it;</hi> if any <hi>good example</hi> be propounded, <hi>follow</hi> it; yea ſo mind what thou heareſt, as if it were ſpoken <hi>onely to thy ſelf;</hi> and be not like a <hi>childe,</hi> who looking in a <hi>glaſſe,</hi> thinks he ſees <hi>another childs face,</hi> and <hi>not his own.</hi> For <hi>want of application</hi> is the ſole cauſe, that in the midſt of ſo much means, ſo few are converted. Yea there be very few men, that make not the <hi>whole Bible,</hi> and all the <hi>Sermons</hi> they hear; yea the <hi>checks of their own conſciences,</hi> and the <hi>motions of Gods Spirit</hi> utterly ineffectual, for want of wit and grace to <hi>apply</hi> the ſame to themſelvs: Whereas if they would rightly and ingenuouſly apply but one text or two, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.12. &amp; 16.26. or the like unto their own ſouls, as they can unto others (being better able to diſcern <hi>others motes, then their own beams</hi>) they might be ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly happy.</p>
               <p>And ſo much of <hi>Non-preaching,</hi> now of <hi>Unpreaching Miniſters;</hi> who as much excell theſe, as the <hi>Spider</hi> excells the <hi>Butterfly.</hi> The ones Sermons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like that <hi>unbleſt food, Hag.</hi> 1.6. the other like thoſe <hi>bitter</hi> and <hi>vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous waters,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 2.19, 20, 21. Or that <hi>Pottage,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 4.39, 40, 41.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170108:23"/>wherein was put <hi>colloquintida:</hi> as you will acknowledge when you have ſeen them in like manner cut up and anatomized: which will be the <hi>ſum of the ſecond part of this diſcovery;</hi> which had been joined with it, onely I prorogue the <hi>printing of that,</hi> until I ſee the <hi>acceptance of this:</hi> becauſe I much queſtion, whether thoſe it concerns will be capable of its uſefulneſs: for having <hi>imparted both parts</hi> to ſome of thoſe Non-preaching and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preaching Miniſters, for whoſe ſakes they were both compoſed; though they commend the pieces, yet (ſo <hi>unacqainted</hi> are they <hi>with their own hearts</hi>) they conceive not that there are any ſuch Preachers.</p>
               <p>Now in caſe it ſhall not be printed, and yet of ſome ſhall be deſired; they may pleaſe to read in lew of it, my <hi>Characters of the kinds of Preaching;</hi> publiſhed fourteen years ſince, and ſold by <hi>James Crumpe,</hi> in <hi>Little Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomews Well-yard.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOSEPH CARYL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Not to mention any of the literall miſtakes, or miſ-poyntings in each ſheet which are uſuall: At the top of <hi>Page</hi> 15. there was (by what means I know not) a whole line taken out, after the proof was returned: and put at the bottom of <hi>Page</hi> 16. whereby the one place is left defective, and the other marred in the ſence. The words are theſe. <hi>Gold; of Cornucopia, that it hath all things neceſſary for food in it; of Panaces.</hi> And in <hi>Page</hi> 39. <hi>line</hi> 33: there is, <hi>moſt the,</hi> inſtead of <hi>the moſt,</hi> Neither of which faults though very groſſe, were eſpied, vntill moſt of the ſheet was printed off: But the ingenuous Reader will either mend them with his pen, or be ſo charitable as to bear with the Compoſitor: However the Author muſt, or elſe turn the buckle of his Girdle.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
